I'm just going to mark that as done that we've talked about it in notes, all right?
Now let's talk about cherry picking non-null values.
And what this means is with Dart, you can easily ask the language to give you values
that are not null.
And I'll explain what this actually means.
Let's say that you have a string, a final string, first name, and it is equal to foo.
Now let's just say this is a constant, all right?
That's what the suggestion was, you see?
I wrote final because I was not planning to reassign this first name value to anything
But then I got a suggestion to actually use the keyword const as you can see here.
So let's say const, all right?
Now what we want to do here, then, is to also create a last name or a middle name, r, and
then we say last name, and I have to change the last name to last name, right?
Actually, what we're going to do is we're going to say the first name is null, all right?
So first name null, middle name bar, and last name bass.
Now if you want to, if you have these values and you want to, for instance, I mean, right
now you can actually see the values that you put here, but sometimes these values are passed
to your function, so you don't know what they are.
Right now you can see what they are, so it's easy.
If I told you, pick the first non-null value, then you would say middle name because you
can see it.
However, if you had a function, for instance, test here that accepted those values, for
instance, string, first name, string, last name, and then string, or yeah, middle name,
etc., then you wouldn't know what those values are, or you cannot make an assumption about
what those values are except that they are nullable or optional strings.
So I hope that you get what I'm trying to say.
If someone told you to pick the first non-null value, one way to do that is, like the old
way of doing that is to say, if first name is not null, then you would say, oh, okay,
first name is the first non-null value, okay?
And then you say, okay, if first name isn't null, then we pick it, otherwise, else, if
middle name is not null, okay?
And then you say, okay, middle name is the first non-null value, and then else, if, again,
last name is not null, then you would print the same thing.
So this is very repetitive.
So it is basically very verbose in the way it is created.
There is a better way of doing this, and that is with the question mark, question mark operator
in Dart, which is available in some other programming languages such as Swift as well.
So the way to do that, then, is you would want to pick the first non-null value.
So you would say, final or const first non-null value, and you would say that's equal to first
name or or.
So this is kind of like question mark, question mark, middle name, and then question mark,
question mark, last name.
So, and, I mean, we're getting a warning here just because Dart understands already that
this middle name, although a, so, this is, although an optional, basically, it has a value.
But if we meet this null, so, and that warning goes away, but, I mean, it would probably
be cleaner if we actually pass these as parameters into this function so we don't get these weird
warnings.
But the way the question mark, question mark operator is working is that it says, it is
an infix operator, just so you know, in, from chapter four, you know, an infix operator is
an operator that has two things, one on each, on each side, the right and left.
So in this case, on the right side, we have middle name, and on the left side, we have
first name.
So what this operator does, it says, if the value on my left side is null, I'm going to
pick the value on my right.
Okay.
And let's now, in this case, say, okay, middle name is not null.
So what it does, it says, first name, are you null?
Yeah, you're null.
Then I'm going to go to the right side.
Middle name, are you null?
Nope, I'm not null.
Then it's going to pick that, and the rest of the statement is not going to be executed.
However, if middle name was also null in this case, then what happens is that it begins
from the left, it says, first name, are you null?
Yes.
Middle name, are you null?
So this entire operation here, it doesn't yield any value.
So this entire operation will let me know.
So it says, okay, now I have to compare our left-hand side.
Are you null?
Yeah, we know that this entire thing was null.
And then it says, right-hand side, are you null?
Nope, I'm bass.
Then it picks bass.
So this question mark, question mark operator is a null-aware operator that picks either
the left side or the right side, whichever one is not null first in that order.
So left side, are you null?
If you're null, I go to the right side.
But if you're not null, I'll pick you.
So keep that in mind.
It is a very handy operator, and it will shorten your code quite a lot.
All right?
Now, if we then go in here and say first, null, null value, you can see it actually says,
oh, it's a string.
However, if these were parameters, so if we said first name, and then string, last name,
sorry, middle name, last name, so they were not provided to us like that,
contour was okay, and then we say final.
Now, if we say first, non-null value, in this case, since it is a normal case, excuse me,
where the Dart compiler isn't working with constants,
then it cannot resolve this to a constant value at the moment.
So it says, okay, there are three optional values.
I have no idea what they are.
So I'm going to do my best to pick the first non-null value depending on, I mean,
based on what we provided here.
However, I may not be able to solve this.
So the final result here, as you'll see, is an optional string, meaning that, well,
I may not be able to resolve this, meaning that this entire operation on top on line nine
may result in a null.
All right?
Sorry about that.
Sorry about my voice.
So that is the question mark, question mark operator.
So I'm just going to mark that we talked about it in my notes.
Okay.
So that was that.
Now, let's talk about the next topic, which is the null aware assignment operator.
I think that's its actual official name.
This operator is very similar to the question mark, question mark operator in that it
tries to resolve a variable to make sure it is not null.
It's going to do its best.
And let's have a look at an example.
Let's just say bar.
I'm going to say, actually, let's just say string and name is first name.
So we begin, we say that we have an optional name and we begin by assigning first name to it.
So it means that its name might, at the moment, depending on the value of first name, it may be
null.
Now, if that is null, you may want to assign another value to it.
All right?
And then you can do that with this operator.
You would say last name.
Let's see what happened here.
We'll try to, oh, is it this?
Yes, it is equal to.
So I actually should change this case to equal to question mark.
Yes.
And I'm going to bring it up again so that it is actually correct, let's say.
And then name equal to, isn't this working?
Last name, oh, where was it this one?
Try changing the,
is it like this?
I'm actually a bit unsure right now.
So let's have a look, actually, what this does.
And it's a three-positional.
And then we say null, null, null, and then bar, and then bass here, okay?
So first name is null, middle name is bar, and last name is bass.
And to be honest with you, I mean, this is quite a lot for me as well.
It is something that is like the syntax of the programming language.
It is something that you will kind of need to live with.
You're not going to memorize this all just in your head all the time.
Of course, like the main parts of it, you're going to remember, but not all of it.
So, and you can see for me as well, I'm just like at the moment, okay, which one is it?
So I'm going to test that.
So to begin with, we say name is first name.
And if that is null, then assign, actually, let's just say middle name,
name here, then use middle name, and then print the name finally.
And I can see it says bar here.
So it's actually question mark, question mark equal.
So I actually maybe need to edit this text one more time.
So I'm just going to say question mark, question mark equal.
Bring it up because I think question mark equal is not going to work.
An equal question mark isn't going to work either.
It's not a valid syntax.
So question mark, question mark equal.
Sorry about that.
So what this operator at the moment is doing is says that I'm going to take
the value on the left-hand side and check whether it is null or not.
If it is null, then I'm going to assign the value on the right-hand side to the left-hand side.
If it is not null, I'm going to leave it alone.
So at the moment, first name, as you saw here, is null,
the first parameter that we pass here.
What it says is, okay, I'm going to check then for middle name if name is null.
And it is null.
And then it says, okay, middle name, are you present there?
And then we'll assign that value here.
So it will be basically it will be bar, which is the value of the middle name.
Now, if we in here said middle name is also null,
right, you could have another operator here that says, okay, if after taking the middle name,
we are still null, then take the last name.
So, and you can see Baz gets printed to the screen.
And that is because because Baz is the last parameter that we're checking on line 10.
And its value is not null.
So you can see how like if I then went here and actually said the value is not null,
the first name is bar.
Then you will see that that will be the value that gets printed to the screen here.
Because right here, name or first name, which is bar, got assigned to name.
So it is an optional string, but it has a value, which is bar.
Then when you come to this line number nine, then you're telling Dart,
look, if name is null, then assign middle name to it.
And Dart says, well, name is a null, it is bar.
So I'm not going to assign middle name to it.
And then it goes to line number 10 and does the exact same thing.
All right.
So that is like the null aware assignment operators.
And it is useful.
I personally, I mean, to be honest with you, I,
as you could kind of guess, I don't use this operator so often.
It is there.
And I have no shame in saying that pretty much in none of my programs have I had to use this.
It is present for you to use.
It is available if you want to use it.
So just don't be like me, but try to remember the syntax is question mark, question mark equal.
And I'm going to actually fix that in my notes as well,
that it is question mark, question mark equal.
And I'm going to check it in the notes that we've talked about it.
Now, let's talk a little bit about conditional method or property access or conditional invocation.
Now, as we talked about in the previous chapter, with Dart, as like many other
programming languages, you can use the dot syntax in order to access or drill down inside properties
and methods or functions inside other objects.
As we saw, for instance, with the case of lists in Dart, you can say,
I have a list and then you want to get its length, then you would say
the name of the list dot length.
And that drills down inside that list and gets the length property.
However, as you saw earlier in this chapter, in chapter number five,
even lists or pretty much any data type in Dart can also be nullable.
So how do you access properties of a null object?
So let's have a look at that now.
Let's say I'm going to actually delete these properties, the parameters that come here to
our function, and I'm going to say, and I'm going to go down here and remove these parameters as
well.
And in here, let's just create an optional list of strings.
Not optional list of optional strings, but just an optional list of valid strings.
Okay.
So I'm just going to say list of strings as an optional list, and I'm just going to say names,
and that is equal to, let's just say at the moment, foo.
All right.
Now, here, if you try to say final length of names or number of names is names, length, okay?
If you then look at the data type here, I mean, we could actually say this is null.
And you can see here, Dart actually is allowed to or is able to give you an error knowing that this
list is null at the moment.
However, if you accept it, I think it's actually better that we accept this value as a parameter
so that Dart analyzer cannot be too smart about making assumptions about what this actually is
at the moment.
So you can see the analyzer is telling you it cannot be unconditionally accessed because
the receiver can be null, and that means, yeah, exactly as it says, it says names can be null.
I don't know if it's null right now or not, but it can be.
So how do you access that?
One way to do that, like, the old way of doing that is to say if names is not null,
then length is names length, okay?
Final length is names length, okay?
So that tells Dart that, look, I'm actually checking for null values,
or I'm checking that this list is not null on line 8, and if it is not null,
then I will access its length property.
And this is kind of, it's called type promotion, and type as in data type.
So in this case, you can see on line number 8, or now if I go and create a new line on
number, on line number 8 and I say names, this is an optional list
that can contain strings, and in here, you can see it is type as the same, but it is promoted
to not being null because you've already checked for it, because if you remove these lines of code,
you can see now that you get an error, the exact same line, but if you check first for null,
and you don't get the error, it's a type promotion, okay?
So this is kind of like the old way of doing that.
So let's say that you want to have, you want to extract the length, so you say final length,
or ints length, right? You create the variable, but you don't assign anything to it.
Then you say if names is not null, then the length is equal to the name's length.
Otherwise, length is zero, okay? So this is one way of doing that.
It's the old way of doing that.
And you may be trying to be smart as well and say, okay, I don't need this else statement if I just
say this is a variable, and by default, it's zero, and yeah, you would be right, because length is
zero by default, and then if names is not null, then you say, okay, length is equal to name's length.
However, there's a better way of doing that, and that is using the dot question mark,
I believe, or the question mark that actually it is, yeah, operator, which conditionally executes
or invokes a method or a property inside an optional if that optional value is present.
I'm going to show you how to do that. So if we say final length
is names, and then you would put question mark dot, and then you would say length,
and you would say, okay, length is equal to name's length, and then you would say
question mark dot, and then you would say length, and you would see this code being
executed without a problem. However, if you go here, you would see that length is an optional
value, is an optional integer. So you may be like, okay, how do I solve that? How do I say that
I want length to be zero if this length value is null, meaning that if the names list is null and
we can't extract the length, then I want this value to be set to null. And that is using our
question mark, question mark operator that we talked about, the null operator that we talked
about earlier, the infix operator. So you could just do this. You would say length is if the names
list is present, meaning that its value is not null, then grab its length. Otherwise, take the
value of zero and assign its length. And if you go to line number nine now and I say length, you can
see it's an integer. So it's not an optional integer anymore. So you could do the same thing
as well. Like you could say names, and you could do the same thing with properties, and you could
also do it for functions. So you can say names, add, adds, right? So you see this is a function
and then we're adding the value of bass to that list. However, you can't unconditionally invoke
this function on an optional value because it might be null. All right? So that is like a very,
very important bit of learning about darts, learning about optionals in darts, how you could use
nullable values. And as you will see, and we'll talk about more in this course, there is many
cases where you have to take into consideration null values. And especially if you're working
with different libraries where the library cannot make too many assumptions and your code is
dependent on that library and you will have to take into consideration, okay, the absence of
a value means that I personally have to take some decisions in my code consciously in order to
execute bits and pieces of code depending on the absence or presence of the value. So try to use
these optional null aware operators that I taught you here, which was the null aware, basically
the decision making to pick, like the in fix operator that tells you whether the left hand
side or the right hand side, depending on which one is not null first, it picks that one, okay?
That operator is very important and the all aware invocation operator, which is here, so you see
some object which may be null, then do something on it. Or the operator, which is a null aware
assignment operator that assigns the value on the right to the variable on the left should the
variable on the left be null, all right? So these are very, very important to understand.
Okay, now that we've talked about that, I'm going to take that in my notes that that is a topic we
talked about. Now, we also have very, very good official documentation about null safety in Dart.
So I'm going to bring up this documentation on a separate screen, and then I'm going to bring it
up here so you can actually see as well, all right? You can see here it says understanding
null safety, and this is great, great documentation about how null safety in Dart works. As you can
see, a lot of examples. I mean, it talks about like from the absolute beginning,
what it actually means, and you can see here null is at the level of object, so it's not,
null itself is not like an object. So you have lists and doubles and integers here,
but null sits on top for itself, kind of like the absence of a value.
So there's lots of examples in this link, and I highly encourage you to have a look at it.
Some things you may not understand, for instance, like this one, you will understand easily because
it says there is something called a thing, like a class, but we haven't talked about classes yet,
and it's name, parameter name here in this function called show gizmo is called thing,
show gizmo is called thing, and you can see it is conditionally accessing a property on that thing.
And then if that property in itself is null, it conditionally access that as well. So this
property is nullable, and then it's accessing another property inside that nullable property
if it's not null. So I mean, it's a great way you can chain them, as you can see here.
Then so if this thing is not null, then conditionally accesses this property on that.
So it's beautiful. I mean, and this thing is available on many other languages like Rust
and Swift as well. So it's nothing new, but it is kind of like such an important topic to understand
in Dart that I think you shouldn't just skim over it. So you should just really learn how to work
with it. All right. We've now talked about null values. So I'm going to take that in my notes
here. Now, I think for chapter five, this information is enough so that we can move on to
the next chapter. And in the next chapter, chapter number six, we're going to talk about some really,
really juicy stuff. And this is like chapter six is going to be like, as I can see in my notes,
I've pressed in a lot of really interesting topics such as enumerations, classes, objects,
custom operators, constructors, factory constructors, class methods, I mean, inheritance
and subclassing, abstract classes. So as you may have heard, depending on what background you have,
you may be like a product owner or product designer, a UXer or whatever. You may not have
like a software engineering background, but Dart in its core is an object-oriented programming
language. It means that things in Dart are objects. An object is an instance of a class,
as we'll talk about in the next chapter. So for you to understand Dart and how these things work,
for instance, we've talked about lists and actually typing dots in front of the name of
list and getting its length, but you may not really know how that works. So in order to
understand all those things, what that dot means, you need to understand what objects are. And in
order to understand objects, you need to know what classes are. And when you understand classes,
then you will learn about inheritance and then we'll talk about abstract classes, properties,
static functions, all that. So what we're going to talk about in chapter six is so important that
I believe that every Dart developer needs to know about this. And we're learning all of these things
to become good at doing Flutter. So although you can go and write like servers, maybe server
applications with Dart, or you could write command line applications with Dart, but these days,
Dart is primarily used for writing Flutter applications. And I don't have any data to
prove that, but I can see for myself when I'm in the community that most people are using Dart
primarily to write Flutter applications. So we're doing all of this to learn more about Flutter.
And I highly recommend that you don't skip these chapters where we're talking about Dart,
especially if you're new to Flutter development. So with that said, let's leave this chapter
the way it is right now. Chapter number five, we're done with that. Let's go to chapter number
six and learn about Dart enumerations and objects. Welcome to chapter six of this Flutter course.
In this chapter, we're going to talk about Dart enumerations and objects. These are some of my
favorite things to actually talk about. So in most programming languages, actually you have the same
facilities. So if you follow along with the other chapters, then you should have a working
Dart project set up now and maybe running in an emulator or a simulator so that you have
the ability to press command S on Mac or control S in Linux and Windows in order to rerun your
project. So without you having to pretty much do anything. So let's then get started. I'm just
going to make that assumption that you're already set with those requirements.
So let's start by talking about enumerations and I'm going to bring up the project from
the previous chapter. Let's just make sure that it's on the screen so you can easily see it.
Now I'm going to go to this list function that we created, remove the only parameter there and
remove that as well. So if I press command S now, nothing should happen on the screen because we
don't have any functionality in test. So let's talk about enumerations and what they actually are.
As you can see here, enumerations are named list of related items. Now, an enumeration is
kind of like equivalent of making a string written programmatically so that it becomes an entity.
And by that, I mean that let's say you have the value name and then you could say foo.
And you would also say const other name. That's also foo. They're both the same string, but they're
not the same identity in that. I mean, internally, actually, in terms of const, I don't want to go
too much into how the compiler actually works, but they're kind of going to be the same string.
But I mean that you've written it twice, so it's not the exact same thing. You have to write it
twice. So an enumeration tries to basically make sure that a value has a name that can be
programmatically referred to. So let's say enum, and that's a keyword in Dart. That's how you
create an enumeration. I'm going to take this that we've talked about some of the things
during the intro. Sorry about that. I have to look at my notes. Anyway, so we have the enum here.
That's how you create an enumeration in Dart. And you would then give a name to your enumeration.
And unlike variables and constants that are written with camel case, you'd have to basically use
another case in here, which is the first letter of every word in your enumeration's name has to be
uppercase, and the rest of the letters have to be lowercase. So let's in this case, for instance,
say person properties, the properties of any person. Then in this enum, you will write the
different properties, for instance, first name, last name, age. So what that basically means is
that you've now defined a list of related things, such as first name, last name, age, which are
categorized under a particular name, which in this case, person properties. And you can refer
to these in your code using the dot notation. So you can say person, properties, dot, first name.
And you can print it, actually. So I'm just going to press Command S and you can see it being printed
to the screen. So enumerations are really, really great as we go on in learning about Dart and how
Dart works, how we can work with Flutter, how we can parse data that comes back from a server,
for instance. But for now, it's enough for you to understand that you can categorize related items
under an enumeration so that you can refer to them later, okay? And in Dart, you can also get
the string representation of these values using their name property. That is something that's
created for you by default. So if you just say name, you now see first name being printed to
the screen as a string. But before that, if you printed the enumerations in on value here for
first name, it would print out the entire thing, okay? So that's short and sweet about enumerations.
We're going to use them quite a lot, actually, especially later where we go to more advanced
topics as we develop our real application. But for now, just know that this is how you create
an enumeration using the enum keyword and then the rest of the properties you just put in curly
brackets, okay? So that's for enumerations. Now we need to talk about switch statements. And
actually, let's bring this back and I'm going to change these two properties, let's say, okay?
And let's just say, for instance, animal type. And let's say cat, dog, and then let's say rabbit.
So let's say we have an animal type enumeration. And we want to, and then we, for instance, get
in our function, we say animal type, animal type. So there's a property that we expect
to be passed to our function called animal type and then we name that property animal type with
camel casing here, okay? So if we do that, then we go to our function here where we're calling
the function, you can see that we got an error, meaning that there is a parameter expected of type
animal type and no one's passing that. So at the call site, which is the place you're calling your
function, that's what a call site is known as in programming. So if you're coming from a background
of design or anything that is not software development related, so you wouldn't probably
know so much about this kind of lingo, but a call site is where you're calling a function. So
at this call site, number 19, we're then going to pass an animal type and let's just say
cat in this case, okay? So in here, we could just print that. I'm just going to say animal type.
I'm going to press command S and you can see cat being printed here, okay? Now, if you want to
execute different types of code depending on this animal type, then you could, which is not
recommended, you could use an if statement. So if you just said, if animal type is equal to animal
is equal to animal type cat, you'd say print all I love cats, okay? Else if animal type is animal
dog, then you would say print or you would say dogs are still fluffy or something.
And else if animal type is animal type
and I wish I had. All right, so this is using normal if statements. You say if animal type is
cat, then blah, blah, if blah, blah. Now, it is one way of doing it, but it's not the recommended
way of working with enumerations and the recommended way of working with enumeration,
especially if you're doing like branching code as we're doing here, is using a switch statement. So
let's convert this code to switch. So let's say switch. You put parenthesis, open, close,
and then open, close curly brackets. And in here, you would put your enumeration. So you say animal
type, okay? And the way to handle these different branches then is with the case keyword. You'd say
in the case of animal type, bunny, print bunny, something like this, okay? Case animal type,
cat, print cat. And case animal type, dog, print dog. Just like that, okay?
Now, this is I'm actually grateful that we're getting this error so you can clearly see what
it says. Is that the case should not complete normally, try adding break or return. Now,
what this is saying that you see in many programming languages, just like Dart,
when the program comes here to the case statement, it kind of like falls through to the next line.
And Dart tries to avoid that. So it says, okay, if I handle bunny, then I'm doing some stuff,
but it kind of feels like I'm falling down to the next line after this because you didn't tell me
what to do after the print statement. So you either tell me to completely go out of this function,
go out of the test function by putting the return keyword here. We haven't talked about return
really yet. But you could do that. You could just say, okay, return right after all of these. So
I'm just going to press command S, and you will see cats being printed to the screen, which is
here. But if you didn't have this return statement here, you would get an error. So you either say
return or you would use the break keyword. Now there's a difference between these. Let's put
a print statement here, and I'm going to say function is finished. So I'm kind of expecting
that by executing our code here, our test function here, passing the value of cat at the moment,
that we fall into the switch, we check that this is cat and then print the cat, and then we return.
This is kind of what it is doing. It means that it kind of skips over this print statement,
and you'll see soon. If I say command S, it will just say cat and then we'll return from that.
So this is not really what I wanted. I wanted this switch statement to be executed,
print cat, and then continue after switch. And that's where you use the break statement,
so or the keyword here. So if you say break, it breaks out of the switch statement and then
continues with the rest of the function as you would expect. So if I press command S here,
you say cat, and then function is finished. All right. So switch is the preferred way of working
with enumerations, especially if you're doing branches. So you could also like,
for instance, if in this case you said make sure this is a cat, you could also in this case say,
if animal type is not animal type, cat, and you would return. Okay? You could do this as well.
So this is kind of like a conditional statement that you're putting in the beginning of your
function, making sure that any code executed after line 10 is completely sure that the animal
type is a cat. Okay? So in that case, you may just use a typical if statement so you don't have to
do switches. Okay? But if you're trying to execute special pieces of code depending on
which value this enumeration contains at the moment, then I highly suggest that you use
switch statement instead of if statement. All right? So kind of depends on your use case.
All right? Okay. I'm just going to mark this item as done in my notes.
Now let's talk about classes. All right? Which is one of my favorite topics to talk about, actually.
Well, classes in Dart and in many other languages actually bring this back to
how it was before, make it a test function. All right? Remove the animal type from here.
So classes in Dart are grouping of various functionalities into one packageable piece
of data. And by that, I mean, for instance, let's say that you have a function called run,
another function called breathe, and then you have a person's first name, a person's last name.
Of course, you could go and define these things like this. You could say const first name,
const last name is something like this. Okay? Goes like that. And then you could have
a function, sorry, you would say run, and then you'd have another function called breathe.
And you could do that. But these are functions that are kind of like for us in this particular
case, or at least in my head at the moment, I am imagining these functions to be related to a person.
The person can run, that person can breathe, that person has a first and a last name. So
the grouping of these related things is done with a class in Dart, at least. So
the way to do that is you would say, for instance, class, which is a keyword in Dart.
The name of the class. Now, for the naming of classes and enumerations and any other
entity except for variables and constants, you should use just normal casing. I don't actually
know if it's called Pascal casing or I think so. But you would just use your uppercase,
the first letter of every word. Okay? So let's just say person. Okay? This is how you would say
a person class. All right? So I don't think actually we can put constants in there. I'm
just going to grab these two functions and just place them inside this person class. All right?
And let's in this, say, print, running, run function, and for breathing, we're going to say
breathing. All right? And in the test function, you would want to create something called an
instance of this class. Now, instances are objects, and objects are created from classes. So
you need to understand how instantiation works in software development. And this is for any
programming language such as Dart, Rust, Swift, Python, JavaScript, where they allow you to create
classes. And now that you know what a class is, in order to use a class, you need to usually
create something called an instance of that class. That means that you tell
the programming language that, okay, here is the class. I know about that. But give me a copy of
it. So every class can be instantiated, meaning that the Dart compiler will create a copy of that
exact class with its data, its functions, its properties, and give that copy to you. All right?
So that is called instantiation. And it works by using the equal sign and creating, putting
parentheses at the end of the name of the class, as I'll show you here. So let's just say final.
And we say person, which is the name of our variable in this case, is equal to,
as I said, equal sign. Then you would write the name of the class and parentheses just like that.
So now you said a person variable in this case is an instance of that person class. Now you'll
understand using dots and notation, you could say person dot run. You see? That function is now
available on your instance of the person class. And you would say person dot breathe. Okay? So
these are functions that are available at instance level of the person class. I know there's a lot
of words that I'm just talking about, but I think you understand the point here. So this is how you
instantiate the person class, and this is how you invoke various functions on that class. So if I
press command S, you can see it says running and breathing. If you said, in this case, person,
and then without instantiating using the parentheses, if you said breathe, you will get
an error here. Instance member breathe can't be accessed using static access. Okay? And that's,
I mean, that is kind of like instance member is an important term also to remember. And instance
member means some functionality that is only available at the instance level, meaning that
it's not available at the person class level, but you have to make a copy of person in order to be
able to access that. All right? So that's the basic of classes. You can do a lot with classes,
as we will talk about soon. So I'm just going to leave that person class right there, and then
just kind of mark that as talked about in my notes as well. And let's now talk a little bit
about objects. Well, objects are actually quite easy to explain. An object is an instance of a
class. So you wouldn't like, when someone says, oh, here's an object of type string, it means
literally that there is a class called string, I've created an instance of it, and that is an
object. So the words instance and object are usually used interchangeably. But if you hear
someone say instantiate a class, then you would say, okay, what's the class name? Oh, it's person.
All right. Person. Now I created an instance. Okay? And in this case, you can see I'm just
creating an instance of person without actually doing anything with it. So that's kind of like
a useless object, all right? But if I put, I say foo is a person, then this foo now is an object
of type person. And actually, you can write its name here, and you'll see that it tells you that
this is a person, okay? So that in short is what objects are. And I can see in my notes that
objects are kind of like in the wrong place. I'm going to bring it to the right place. Sorry about
that. Okay? Now let's talk a little bit about constructors. And I can see constructors also
at the wrong place in my notes, so I'm going to bring those also to the right place. Okay?
Sorry about that. What a constructor is at its name, as its name indicates, is a special logic
in a class that constructs or initializes or builds that class's instance, all right? So
you may say that, okay, let's go to our function here, to our class here, person.
And let's say every person has a first name or a name, okay? So let's just define that. We say
final string name, all right? As you can see now, Dart is saying, okay, you said that every person
has a name, and it's a final, meaning that after the person has been instantiated or after that
person has been initialized or created an instance from, you cannot change that name because you said
final, all right? If you said string name is foo, that would be different because it means
every person instance that gets created has the default value foo for its name. That's a completely
different way of saying what the name of the person is. In this case, as you can see, we're
saying that every person instance, every person copy that we create has a name. Now Dart is saying,
okay, where is the name then? You didn't tell me how to create it. And that's where you would
want to use something called constructor, okay? Constructors are sometimes called as initializers.
Depending on the background of the programmer, they may call it constructor initializer
or maybe some other names that I don't know about. But if you hear that, a constructor,
then you will now know what I'm talking about soon actually. So now what you can do, at least
in Visual Studio Code, when you get this error is to just hover over it and then press command
on Mac or control on Windows or Linux and press dot. Now you will see you will get some suggestions
here. And the second suggestion, at least for me here, it says create constructor for final
fields, okay? And I can just press that. And what happens here now, you see it's that it creates
something that looks kind of like a function, but it doesn't have a name. Its name is implicitly
set to the name of the class, okay? So basically, it says I'm a special function with the same name
as the class, and I expect a value to be given to me, which I will then in turn assign to the name
property of myself. It's kind of like a strange way of doing things, but is quite clean as well,
okay? After you do that, so this is how you create a constructor. After you do that, then at the call
site where you're calling this person class to create an instance of it, it will complain saying
that, oh, I'm expecting an argument, but I didn't find any. And that's where you have to pass the
name. So let's say in this case is foo bar, okay? And then on the next line, you can just say print
foo name, all right? And press command S, and then you can see foo bar being printed to the screen.
So that is like the basic of a constructor. That's how you construct instances of your class,
all right? Now, you may be saying that, all right, I don't want, I mean, you can do many fancy things
with constructors. You could say, okay, its name, for instance, by default, must have a special
value. You could do that. There's lots of things you can do with constructors, which I'm not going
to go into the details of. But right now, just know that a constructor is this special kind of
function that has the same name as the name of the class, and then parentheses, and then you put your
values in here, all right? Okay, that was constructors. Now, let's talk a little bit about
methods, all right? And what methods are, I'm actually going to go here and say, we're going
to talk about methods. I know it's at the wrong place in my notes as well. Sorry about that.
A method of a class we've talked about already, to be honest with you, and a method of a class is
a function on the class, which is usually referred to as an instance method, meaning that the
function is available after you've instantiated that class, all right, as we're doing in line
number 14. Name is an instance variable. So, is a variable that is available at an instance level
is not an instance method. An instance method should be a function, all right? So, let's go
and create a function here that doesn't return any value denoted by the void return type, and we
say print name, all right? The functionality of this function is only just to print the name of
the class, all right? That's all it does. And in Dart, you're also, now that we're talking about
this, I'll just mention also that in Dart it's usually better not to prefix your instance
variables or instance functions inside the class itself using this keyword. This keyword in Dart,
the this this or that this keyword basically refers to the current instance of this class,
all right? So, you can either tell print name to print this dot name, or it's actually better
to remove this and refer to it as name. That's the recommended way of doing it, okay? So,
avoid the keyword this as much as you can unless you have to. And we'll come to those points
hopefully later in this course why you may have to do that, why you may have to use this.
All right. Now we have the print name instance method, all right? So, let's just use it. Instead
of this print function that we're doing here, let's just say foo dot print's name, all right?
Command S or Control S on Linux and Windows and Command S on Macintosh, and then you get the
Flutter foo bar printed here. Or you could just say print, I'm going to, I will now print the name
of this person in single quotes. We don't need double quotes, okay? Command S and you will see
that message being printed here, followed by the actual name of that instance. So,
if someone says method or instance message, you will then know what we're talking about.
It's a function created at the class level that does some stuff, all right? So, that's short and
sweet. Okay. Now that we've talked about that, let's talk a little bit about inheritance and
subclassing. I'm going to bring the caption here so you know what we're talking about.
Now, inheritance and subclassing are so, so important in Dart and in any other object-oriented
programming language that I don't think anybody should jump over it. Like, for instance, I know
developers working in various programming languages that are object-oriented, but they kind of steer
clear of the object-oriented aspects of that language. Maybe they don't need it and maybe
they just feel like it's unnecessary or they feel like, oh, it's just too complicated.
But in Dart, if you want to become a good Flutter developer or a good Dart developer, you need to
know about classes and inheritance. So, let's talk about inheritance. What inheritance in Dart is,
is that it allows you to define a class and then to add more functionality to that class
into a new class. So, let's, for instance, say we go into our test function here and remove that,
okay, that code, and also remove the person class. Now, let's create a class living thing,
all right, and then we say void, breathe, and then we say print. Living thing is breathing,
okay? So, we created a class living thing, and we're saying that anything that lives needs to
breathe. Now, this may be an assumption, but anyways, anything that lives and is above the
ground and is basically alive is breathing, okay? So, that's our function on the living thing. Now,
you may say, okay, any living thing may also have the ability to move, okay? Then we have
a function called move. I'm going to say print, I am moving, all right? So, now you may say, okay,
now I kind of want a class called cat, all right. Cat is also a living thing. One way to do that,
to go about creating a class, the cat class is to say class cat, and then you say, hmm,
I kind of need these functions, and you'll go and copy it, and then you paste them here,
all right? And then you say, okay, I'm good to go now. But one of the absolute paramount qualities
of a developer is that developers do not like to repeat themselves, and it is such an important
concept in programming that you need to avoid repeating yourself, that you need to just coin
that down now, get it straight so that you don't make this mistake as we're doing in this code
right now. So, the first thing you want to do as a developer is say, how can I grab this code?
And it's obvious that the cat is also a living thing. So, that's where you want to use the
extends keyword that allows you to inherit the functionality inside the living thing class
into your cat class. So, in this case, I'm saying cat class extends or read it in English as inherits
living thing, all right? So, you can see that the cat class in itself is empty right now,
but if you go to the test function and I say, final, fluffers is a cat, and then I can say
fluffers, you can see that now that the cat class has breathe and move functionalities,
or functions, actually. So, although cat itself didn't define these functions,
but they're available for the instance in this case called fluffers of type cat to use. So,
you can just say move, and then you can say fluffers, okay? So, if I run this code,
if I delete everything in the debug console and run this code, you can see that the cat
instance called fluffers is saying move, or I am moving, and it will also say living thing is
breathing, okay? Now, we could also talk about, now that we're talking about inheritance and
subclassing. Actually, maybe I shouldn't call it subclassing, but I also think it's important
for you to understand what subclassing is. Subclassing is literally the same thing as
inheritance. Subclassing is saying that you have a class and you're creating a subcomponent, like a
subthing of it, which may actually have, it's a little bit of a strange name in sub because
sub means kind of like a subset of things available in that class, but it actually is like a superset
because it will grab everything, like the cat at the moment has every functionality in living thing,
right? But it may not necessarily do that. It's kind of complicated to explain, but if you hear
subclassing or inheritance, know that that is what we mean. You use the extents keyword, usually,
okay? All right. Now, we've talked about inheritance and subclassing.
So, I'm gonna move a little bit my notes around, sorry about that, that I'm looking away from the
screen, and now we're gonna talk about abstract classes, all right? There's good documentation
about abstract classes, and what we're gonna do here is to just change this class living thing
at the moment to abstract, and you'll see that everything works as expected. Well, an abstract
class is very similar to a normal class, and there's good documentation about what an abstract
class actually is from a Dart perspective, and you can see it says use the abstract modifier to
define an abstract class that cannot be instantiated, all right? So, an abstract class is just like a
normal class that can't have instances. So,