and try to follow along with the steps provided.
So after you've done all of this,
you should be able to be anywhere on your computer
and just say Flutter doctor.
Now Flutter doctor is a very important command
because it looks at your Flutter installation
and it kind of makes sure that it's in good health,
as denoted by the word doctor.
So because Flutter in itself is a framework
and it depends on many other bits and pieces
which your computer may need to have
in order for Flutter to actually work optimally,
Flutter doctor will then go through a series of steps
to ensure that first Flutter is updated
and that you for instance have Android tool chain
that you have Xcode installed, Chrome, blah, blah.
So I mean, this result at the moment
looks quite fine on my computer,
but if you're running Flutter doctor
for the first time on your computer,
you may get a few problems.
Some of the problems that you will experience probably
is gonna say Android SDK couldn't be found,
Xcode couldn't be found,
because if you're running Flutter on a Windows machine
or a Linux machine, then you can't have Xcode.
Xcode is like the software provided by Apple.
And only runs unfortunately on Mac OS
and it's used for compiling or creating Mac OS,
iOS and iPad OS pieces of software.
So although you can run Flutter on your Linux
and on your Windows machine without a problem,
you won't be able to produce or test your Flutter code
running on an iPhone, unfortunately,
unless you have access to Xcode.
And the easiest way to get access to that is of course,
to have a Macintosh.
And that's unfortunate because yeah,
it's just not available for other platforms.
So you've run Flutter doctor and it's basically gonna tell you
that, okay, now I'm gonna assume that you're on a Macintosh.
It's gonna tell you that, okay, Xcode, for instance,
you need to install Xcode.
And the way to do that is you need to open App Store
on your computer and just type Xcode here
and go and install Xcode on your computer.
So depending on, I don't know which version
is the latest at the moment,
but if you're trying to develop Flutter app to be able
to run on your iOS phone or the iOS simulator,
then you need to install Xcode.
If you're on a Macintosh, sorry,
if you're on a Linux computer or Windows,
you don't have to do this step.
Actually, you can't do unfortunately this step.
So once you've done that,
you also need to make sure that you've installed
developer tools for Xcode.
So you need to install Xcode.
Developer tools for Xcode.
So let's see how we can do that.
Developer tools, Xcode.
Command line tools, right.
Let's see, install from terminal,
there's a command that you can execute in order to do that.
And that command actually looks like this.
Here, I will zoom into it so you can see better.
It says sudo xcode select install.
So you need to issue that command in your terminal.
So if I do that and it says, what's the password,
I'll enter my password and it says they're already installed.
So if you haven't done that,
please go ahead and execute this command
in order to install command line tools for your Xcode.
Now, the next piece after Xcode that you will need is
let's see if I can actually bring up.
So we've talked about Flutter Doctor,
that was Flutter Doctor.
And we also talked about installing Xcode.
So I'm now bringing that up a little bit late.
But now the next step is to install Android Studio.
So what Android Studio is, is like the equivalent of Xcode,
but for writing Android specific applications.
Now, in order to write Flutter applications,
you don't need Android Studio per se,
but you kind of need the SDK manager.
Now, both iOS and Android,
for programmers, they provide you with something called an SDK,
just like Flutter is an SDK or toolkit.
iOS and Android also provide you with SDK
in order to write native applications.
And since Flutter utilizes these native capabilities
of each platform in order to, for instance,
create an application that's compatible with iOS or Android,
it will utilize the native components, sorry,
or the native pieces of software,
namely called Xcode, sorry,
namely called iOS SDK and Android SDK.
So you need to download Android Studio
so you get access to the SDK manager
so you can install an Android SDK.
Now, Xcode in itself,
when you download the latest version of Xcode,
it comes with the latest version of the iOS SDK,
but Android Studio doesn't do that.
Well, wait a minute.
Yeah, it probably does in the latest versions,
but we can check that out.
So if you go to your browser and just say Android Studio,
and then you open up developerandroid.com.
Let's just go there.
And then you can just click on download Android Studio,
and then there are download options,
and you can see there's available for Windows, Mac, and Linux.
So then please go ahead and download your Android Studio,
and I can see for Macintosh is a package,
so you can install it easily.
You don't have to unzip anything,
and for Windows is also like an executable,
so tar.gz as well for Linux.
So now let's say that you've done that.
Now, after doing that,
then you should be able to bring up Android Studio.
Let's see.
I'll bring it up here.
Now, when you bring up your Android Studio,
it will just pretty much be empty here on the screen,
and you'll get some tips and tricks
how to use Android Studio.
But the important thing for you here
is to be able to install the Android SDK.
So if you go then to tools,
I believe there is an SDK manager right here.
So just ensure that you have an SDK installed.
For me, I have Android 12 installed here.
So ensure that you have one of these SDKs
ready for you to use by Flutter.
And as soon as you've done that,
then when you run then your Flutter doctor command,
then the part about Android SDK is going to be ticked here.
Sorry, the Android Studio.
So that's that.
So we've talked about the Android tool chain,
which is the Android SDK you can see.
We've talked about Xcode.
Chrome is just a web browser.
If you want, you can have that.
If you're developing Flutter applications for the web,
it kinda is necessary.
And then you can run Flutter.
And then this, you're probably,
if you're just getting started with Flutter,
you're not gonna have this VS Code part ticked
because VS Code is a code editor,
an open source code editor provided by Microsoft.
And it is the code editor
that I'm gonna use for the entire course,
for this entire course as we go on.
And to be honest with you,
I've tried Android Studio
and I've tried VS Code for Flutter development
and I can highly recommend that you use VS Code
just for its sheer performance,
it's for its simplicity, extensions,
and its ability just to really focus on a simple editor
without bothering you with lots of bells and whistles.
So it's a preference though.
Some people use Android Studio for Flutter development
and some people use VS Code.
So I don't think one is better than the other.
It's completely a preference.
So that's for Android Studio and the Android SDK.
So now let's go ahead and install Visual Studio Code,
which is the tool that I'm gonna use for this course.
So let's bring up a new window
and I'm gonna say, install Visual Studio Code.
And I'm gonna bring the window up here so you see.
Let's go here and you can download the one that you prefer
for your computer, I've chosen Mac.
And for me specifically,
I have a Macintosh with an Apple Silicon.
So I then choose this one Mac with an Apple Silicon
and then it's gonna download that for you automatically.
So it's just about 200 megabytes, I think,
or actually 100 megabyte only.
After you've done that just on a Macintosh,
you would go and put that on in your applications folder.
So I'm actually gonna delete that,
which I downloaded just now
because I already have VS Code on my system.
So that's for Visual Studio Code.
So let's go ahead now, now that we've done that,
I'm gonna talk a little bit about some extensions
that we're gonna use in Visual Studio Code.
So let me bring up my terminal
and we don't need that.
Let's go and bring up Visual Studio Code.
And then I already actually have
so many Visual Studio Code windows open,
but I can just say new window.
So you see how Visual Studio Code looks like.
And then let's see, don't show again.
Okay, so this is pretty much how Visual Studio Code
looks like, so it's a very simple application to begin with.
Now, what we need to do for this example
is to enable a few extensions.
Now, the first extension that we're gonna enable
is called error lens.
And you need to go here on the left-hand side,
find extensions and just type error,
if I can type error and just say error lens, just like that.
Click on error lens and just press enable or install,
I believe it's called.
So error lens allows you to see errors in line
without you having to click on a specific line
of error, basically.
So it expands the entire error as you're coding,
you will probably have some errors in your code.
That error will be then displayed right there
in front of your face in its entirety.
So you don't have to press a little small button
to be able to see that complete error.
So it's a fantastic extension, to be honest with you.
Now, the other thing that you'll need
is something called bracket pair colorizer.
And that bracket pair colorizer is something
that is already installed in Visual Studio code.
It used to be an extension that you could download,
but it was so popular that Microsoft has added that
internally to Visual Studio code.
So you don't have to do that manually,
sorry, by installing an extension.
Now that we've talked about that,
the next step is to actually install
Flutter and Dart extensions.
So here, just type Flutter.
Let's do that.
And then just click on the install button.
I've already installed that,
so there's a disable button for me here.
The Flutter extension,
and then you'll also need the Dart extension.
So just type Dart and then install that as well.
So after these two installations,
we also need to install another great extension called block.
B-L-O-C.
I'm not gonna go into the details of what block is,
because you will learn about block a lot later in the course,
but it is just a great extension to have.
As we go on, you're gonna learn about it.
So I can't really explain exactly what it is right now,
but just install it,
and I will tell you more about block later
in the course, I promise.
So that was basically installing a block.
Now, when you start up your Visual Studio code,
it probably doesn't look like the way it does for me.
And that is because I have a custom theme
installed on my Visual Studio code called Tokyo Night.
It is a very, very mellow, dark theme, as it's called.
And themes in Visual Studio code can be installed
just like you install an extension.
So if you like my theme,
you're more than welcome to go into extensions
and then search for Tokyo Night and just install it.
So it has different theme colors as well.
This is the one I use, Tokyo Night.
Actually, I use this one, Tokyo Night.
So if you want that theme, please go ahead and install it.
And now that we've talked about that,
we come to the last point that I wanted to discuss basically
before we wrap up this chapter, which is our chapter two.
So now that we talked about a little bit of setup
for setting up your Flutter installation
and setting up your Flutter installation,
and setting up your text editor,
which in this case is Visual Studio code.
In the next chapter, which is chapter three,
we're gonna talk about Dart programming.
So before we actually jump into writing Flutter applications,
we're gonna talk about how to write code in Dart,
or at least understand like the basics of Dart.
So without further ado, let's close up this chapter
and I'll see you in the next one.
Hello everyone, and welcome to the third chapter
of our Flutter course.
In this chapter, I thought maybe we could focus
a little bit on, actually not a little bit,
but quite a lot on Dart.
As you know from the previous chapter,
we know now that Dart is the programming language
that powers Flutter.
So it would be a good idea for us at least
to get a little bit of introduction to Dart,
how it works, a little bit of its internals,
different data types, functions, methods, classes,
but this chapter as well, just like the entire course,
I'm kind of assuming that you haven't done
any programming at all before.
So I'm gonna take things very slowly,
take the concepts one at a time, introduce them to you.
So, and I will give you some references to read more
about the topics as we won't have really that much
of a time in this course to go into detail about everything.
So the goal of this chapter is to basically get you started
with programming Dart and writing your apps
then later for Flutter.
In order to do that, we need to have a project set up.
And by project, I mean, you need to have some kind
of a playground set up so that you can start writing
Dart code and then you can try it on, for instance,
a telephone or a simulator or what have you.
Now, a lot of people would rather go to Dart pad
as we saw in the previous chapter
and start writing their code in Dart pad.
That's one way of doing it.
But since in this course, we're gonna write an application,
release it for iOS and Android,
it is safe to say that we can literally start actually
creating our real project here and now
so that we can then later build upon it
rather than writing all our code in Dart pad
because you can then by doing, by writing your code
in an actual Flutter project, you can get used
to how we work with Flutter as a whole.
So I think this is a little bit of a time invested
into later chapters as well, where we're gonna work
and continue working on the same project.
So we have to just set it up once.
But at the same time, there is a little bit of a value
in not blending in too much of our test code,
like what we're doing in this chapter
with what we're gonna do later in the actual application,
if you know what I mean.
So I think it would be better now for us to set up
just a test application and then keep working on it.
And then later on, when we start doing
the actual application,
then we create a separate project for that.
So now let's then do that together.
So I'm gonna bring my face down here
so you see the entire screen.
I'm then going to create a new terminal window
and bring it up here on the screen so you can see it.
And I'm gonna increase the font
so it's a little bit easier to spot when I'm typing.
So let's go to a folder where you try to,
or where you keep your projects.
For me, I go to dev projects
and I have a folder there called Flutter.
So I try to put all my Flutter projects in here.
Then in order to create a new Flutter project,
what you have to do is to issue the Flutter create command.
And this create command is already shipped inside Flutter.
So if you say which Flutter,
this is gonna go and find the actual Flutter binary.
If you remember from the previous chapters
where we installed Flutter.
It's gonna find the Flutter binary
and then call the create command on it.
So if you say Flutter create,
it expects you to kind of like provide it
with some sort of a name of a project.
So let's just say, learning Dart.
So that's the binary, that's the command
and that is the name of the project.
So this is the easiest way to create a new Flutter project
in my opinion at least.
So let's execute that command.
It's gonna do its thing.
And what I'm gonna do then is to,
I've created a new folder called learning Dart.
So let's go and I'm gonna say, CD learning Dart.
And then I'm going to issue a command called code dot.
And I can actually bring this a little bit to the right
so you can, and also do it like this
so you can see what I'm typing.
As you can see, I've written code dot.
And what code does is that it brings up Visual Studio code.
So it's just like a command that you can issue
in order to bring up Visual Studio code.
And if I just bring up Visual Studio code
the way it is right now, and for instance, you can see it,
you can't see it right now
but it's because I have a separate screen here.
I'll bring up Visual Studio code as you can see here by hand.
There is a good extension or there is an ability
for Visual Studio code to install this code shortcut
for you in terminal in your path.
So if you say which code, it just says user local bin code.
So it's just an executable that allows you then
to open up Visual Studio code with a path.
Like, so you can say open up Visual Studio code
in this folder.
So you can just say code dot, so.
And you can do that in Visual Studio code.
You can allow that to be installed
by doing command shift P on Macintosh or control shift P,
I believe in windows and Linux.
And there's this little command here that says shell command
install code command in path.
So if you execute that once, then it's already set up for you.
You don't have to do that anymore.
So if you'd like to be able to say code dots in terminal
and open the current folder within Visual Studio code
without you having to open Visual Studio code manually
and then doing file open, then I suggest
that you do command shift P or control shift P
in Visual Studio code, depending on which operating system
you're using and then choosing shell command
install code command in path.
So I've already done that, so I can just say code dot
and I'll bring this up here.
So as you can see, this is the basics of a simple
Flutter project that you create with Flutter Create.
Now, Visual Studio code has a built-in terminal,
so I don't have to have this terminal window open anymore.
So I'm just going to close it.
And I'm going to make this full screen,
increase the size a little bit so you can see better.
And perhaps I could even remove this Flutter logo on top right
so you can see the content a little bit better as well.
So that's the creation of our simple Flutter project.
Now, in order for this Flutter project to run
and you be able to run this application
and keep testing your project,
you would have to select a target.
And you do that with command shift P
and then choosing Flutter select device.
So you can just say Flutter select device, enter.
Command shift P is on Macintosh and control shift P
I believe is in Linux and Windows.
So do that, command shift P is a very important command.
You're going to use it quite a lot in this course.
So just learn that please.
Then I'm going to say select device
and I'm going to choose, since I'm on a Macintosh
and as you saw earlier, we have Xcode already installed.
Xcode comes also with the entire iOS SDK
and also with the simulator.
I can choose to run our application on iOS simulator
or I can choose to run it on an actual phone.
Now for this, I believe,
I don't know if we've talked already about SCRCPY
to be honest with you.
I'm just going to search in my notes
to see if you've talked about that.
And if you just give me one second, please just check here.
I believe we're going to set it up in chapter six.
So we haven't set up SCRCPY yet.
So for that purpose, I'm just going to say
select device and I'm just going to say start iOS simulator.
So that is going to, as you can see,
start up iOS simulator.
And that for now is like the best way
for us to test our application.
So while this is connecting,
I can show you a little bit around as well.
We have, as you can see, lots of files here
already created for us.
We're going to go through some of these.
But one of the most important files
that you're going to need to get used to
is this lib slash main.dart.
And this is where the majority of the code is written.
So this is its contents at the moment.
Let's see what it's doing with the simulator.
I'm just going to have a look here.
It's taking a little bit longer than expected.
So what I'm going to do is I'm just going to
kill the iOS simulator manually.
This usually doesn't happen, but that's okay.
If it does happen, then you know how to deal with it.
Just close the simulator.
And then I'm just going to go to Command-Shift-P,
select device, and then start iOS simulator fresh.
So it's starting right now.
Okay, so that's our simulator.
And I'm actually going to decrease the size of this
a little bit since I realized that it is a very large font.
So this is our main.dart file.
This is like where the Flutter command line command
has created, it is the file that has been created for us.
So we don't have to play around with it too much,
to be honest with you, at the moment.
For the purpose of this chapter,
we're just going to have a look at basically kind of like
exploiting this code so that we can inject our code into it
so we can learn Dart a little bit.
So you don't have to understand all of this code
the way it is right now.
There's lots of comments and et cetera.
So that's that part.
So now that we're here and then you can see
we have a little simulator here.
And in order to run this application on this simulator,
since you've already done the Flutter select command,
you just go to run and you say run without debugging for now.
So since the simulator is already selected,
then it understands that it needs to compile this project
for my simulator.
So, and we're just going to give it some time
depending on your machine and like,
what do you have for specifications on your machine?
This command could take anywhere between a couple of seconds
to maybe 30 seconds or even more.
And I'm not sure how long it's going to take
for a fresh Flutter project, to be honest with you,
to start running on the simulator,
but it took about 21 seconds or 22 seconds.
I will bring up the project now.
And this is like the basic Flutter project.
I'm not going to go into details about how it works,
but you can press the plus button if you want to.
But what I'm going to do,
I'm just going to close this widget inspector
that was opened automatically.
And I'm just going to bring this a little bit down
so that we can see the debug console, okay?
So that's for setting up our project.
So that part is done.
Now, the first thing that we need to talk about
when we start talking about Dart is the concept of keywords.
Now, since I'm assuming that you haven't done
any programming language in any other place before,
you need to understand what keywords are.
They're very important in understanding
any programming language, basically.
And keywords are concisely explained.
They're words that are reserved for the programming language
that you cannot use for anything else
than what the programming language intends those words
to be used as.
I know that sounds a little bit difficult,
but I mean, there's no real good analogy
in like if you're coming from Figma,
if you're coming from a design world,
what a keyword could be because in a design world,
you're not really talking in terms of code with your product
or with your software where you're designing your stuff.
But when you come to programming language,
as you know, it's a language.
So words mean stuff in a programming language.
So a keyword is, as its name indicates,
is a word that has a special meaning
in that particular language.
And I'll provide a link here for you that you can check out,
but I'm gonna open it up and bring it to the screen here,
increase the size a little bit so we can see better.
Have a look at my screen here.
And you can see this is part of the documentation
for Dart programming language
that explains what keywords are in Dart.
And you can see there are some words
that have special meaning like show, import,
extends, async, await, break.
So you can say that the language,
the Dart language is made out of these keywords.
That is pretty much it.
It's just like series of keywords,
like the things that you tell the language that,
hey, I wanna do something.
And then it says, okay, what do you wanna do?
Then you say, okay, I wanna do this or this or this.
So special words for the programming language
so that it understands what you mean, basically.
So that's for keywords.
For now, we don't have to really go into so much more details
about what a keyword is, but for now,
just understand that a keyword is a special word
in the programming language's brain,
kind of so that you can talk to it.
It's your interface with the programming language
to make it understand what you wanna do, okay?
And please check out the link that I provided here
to understand more about keywords.
Okay, so we've talked about keywords.
I'm just gonna check it in my notes
so that we know we've talked about it.
Now, the next concept that we need to talk about
are data types.
If you, for instance, come from a design background,
then you have different tools to work with.
For instance, you may have, in your design system,
whatever you're using, if you're using product from Adobe
or if you're using, for instance, Figma or whatever,
Visio or whatever tool you're using,
then there's a set of components that you can work with.
For instance, you can drag in a text field
or you can drag in an image field, sorry, an image,
or you can, for instance, assign a color to a text.
So these are all things that you can do with that software.
Now, a data type in a programming language,
like Dart, is the type of a thing, for instance.
You would say, I have some data in my mind.
Okay, what is it?
It's the first name of my friend.
Okay, his name is Jack or whatever.
And then you would say, okay, what type is Jack?
Is it a number?
No, is it like, is it a list of things?
Well, yeah, it's a list of characters, yeah.
Okay, then that is this data type.
Or you could say, I'm thinking about my age.
My age is, let's say I'm 37.
Okay, what is 37?
Is it a list of things?
Well, yeah, kind of.
It's a list of numbers, a list of digits,
but it's also in itself a number.
So then there has been this convention
in different programming languages,
and every programming language pretty much
that you can use these days has this concept of data types.
Data type is, as its name indicates,
a specific name assigned to a series,
to a series, a specific name assigned to a data
that is bound to be of a specific type as well.
So for instance, in Dart,
you have data types called integers,
or you have strings, or you have arrays and sets,
which we'll talk about soon,
but a data type just for now, no,
it's just a stamp on a piece of data
to say that you're of this specific type.
So you could think of a data type as a nationality.
You could say like every person coming from Sweden
is Swedish, boom, that's his data type.
So it's just a categorization of data
based on their appearance
or based on what they actually hold.
So for instance, you can say,
here's a university full of engineers,
and these are software engineers,
these are mechanical engineers,
so the software engineer is a data type
or is a person type or category type.
So putting stamps on things based on the categorization
is kind of what data type does.
And in short, I mean, you just have to know
that it's just a categorization of things
based on what they hold.
So, and there's a website that you can read
about Dart data types, and it's right here.
I don't know if I've provided it here on the link below,
as you can see Dart Core Library HTML, so.
And here you can read more about Dart data types,
but we're not gonna go into so much detail
about all of these right now.
Just know that data type in Dart is,
or any programming language basically that has data types
is a categorization of data
based on their appearance or contents.
Now, let's talk a little about
something called constants in Dart.
A constant, usually in programming languages
are values whose value cannot be changed.
That's a little bit meta, but let's say for instance,
the value of 10 is a number.
It cannot be changed.
10 is 10, and it will always be 10.
Or your name, that is a constant.
Although you can go and change it,
but as long as that is your name, it is a constant.
So, another example of a, I mean,
there are so many values that can be constants,
which will actually be quite abstract for me
to explain right now, but just know that a constant
is a value whose internal data cannot change
during where you're writing your program,
and also during when you're running your program.
So, that is kind of what a constant is.
But there is also this notion of a compile time constant
and a runtime constant.
And I mean, you don't have to know about
like those different types of constants right now,
just because like in Dart, a constant is a constant,
whether it's runtime or compile time is a constant,
it's just a constant, as you'll see soon.
But I still believe that it's important to understand
the difference between compile time and runtime.
When you're talking about programming,
when you're becoming a software developer,
and I hope by the end of this course,
you'll actually become a software developer
if you're not already, that would be really amazing.
But the notion of a compile time
and runtime is very important to understand.
And developers like to make a distinction
between whether something has happened during compile time
or something has happened during runtime.
And compile time is, or before I explain compile time,
maybe I should explain compile.
Compile is where you take the program
that you're writing here, and you tell the computer
that I want you to package this up
so that I can run it later on X and Y machine.
So that process of packaging things up, simply said,
is in very simple terms, is called compiling
or a compilation, okay?
So from where you start writing your program with a hand
with your fingers until where you package it,
you're pretty much just compiling it, okay?
But when you run it, like we're running it at the moment
on iOS simulator, that session from where you start
outputting your program into this device
and for it to run your program from that moment on,
then the distinction separates into runtime.
So you have then compile time and runtime,
and a constant is a value that is the same
during compile time and runtime.
So its value doesn't change.
So the value of 10 is 10 while you're writing your program
and also stays the value of 10 while the program is running.
So that is a very simple explanation of a constant.
So now let's put constants and data types in practice.
Now, in this project that was created for you
by Flutter Create, in this line of code,
as you can see, it says void main.
We're not gonna talk about exactly what that is,
but just press Enter at the end of it
and just write final,
and I'm gonna tell you what final is.
So, and just saying name is equal to foo, okay?
This is, there's lots going on in here
and I'm gonna tell you what is actually happening here.
But before we actually go through all these details,
let's add something here called a constant.
So I'm just gonna say const age is 27, or yeah, 27.
As you can see, this is how you write code in Dart.
You start by a keyword, usually,
or a variable name or something
as we're gonna talk about it.
But const is a keyword, okay?
And it tells Dart that what is following here is a name.
Right after const, I'm gonna write some name.
And in that name, then I'm gonna basically say,
okay, I'm adding the value of 27 to this age.
I'm sorry about this, my dog also barking a little bit.
So what is happening here is that you're telling Dart
that I'm putting the value of 27 into a constant called age.
And you can refer to this age later.
For instance, you can say then const age twice the age.
You can say it's equal to age multiplied by two.
And this is also a constant because at compile time,
where Dart is basically trying to understand
what you've written, it says, okay, you said 27,
and then you're saying 27 is a constant.
So its value is never gonna change.
And if you tell me 27 multiplied by two,
that also is a constant because both this side
and this side are compile time constants.
So that's what we mean by a constant.
It's a value that is specified during compile time
and it cannot change.
So also it's important to notice that you're learning Dart
and here is, sorry, I have to just tick some items
in my notes to make sure that I've explained
all of those to you.
You can see here that every line of code in Dart
needs to end with a semicolon.
And that tells Dart that, yeah,
you're starting a new line of code.
Of course you can put two lines of code like this,
but if you just press save,
there is a program automatically running in the background
which is called Dart FMT, which is the Dart formatter,
which is gonna format your code and pre-ify it.
So if I put a lot of spaces in here and just press save,
you can see upon doing command S on Mac
or control S on Linux and Windows,
upon saving Dart formatter is gonna kick in
and format the code for you.
So just a little hint.
Okay, those are constants.
So we've talked about that.
Now let's talk about variables a little bit.
A variable is usually anything that contains
a value that is not a constant.
I mean, I think that's the simplest way
of explaining what a variable is.
A variable as a name indicates, it can vary.
And that means that the data that it holds,
it doesn't need to be constantly the same.
It means that from where you start the program,
you may actually assign a value to this variable
and you may also change that variable
depending on what type of variable it is.
So there's also this notion of a final variable in Dart,
which we'll talk about soon.
So before we do that, let's go through this main function
here and you could just say var name is foo.
And here, what I've done is that I've created a variable
indicated by the var keyword whose value is foo,
or let's just say Alex,
and set my column to end the line.
Now, if I wanna change this value,
all I could say here is to say name is equal to Anthony,
or whatever.
Now, this is basically us assigning a new value
to this variable, saying Anthony.
As I said, there is also the notion in Dart
for a keyword called final.
So you could just say final name equal to Alex.
And it's a little bit strange
because final is also a variable
whose value cannot be changed.
So you may be like, okay, what kind of a variable is that?
How is that not a constant?
Now, there's a little limitation
because you may try to like say const name Alex.
But this, as you will see later in the course,
final gives you the flexibility
to assign a value to your variable
a little bit later maybe in the process of creating it,
but it still indicates to Dart
that the value of this variable is not gonna change
after it has been assigned to.
It's a little bit, yeah,
it's just a little bit confusing maybe at the moment.
So let's just say a variable is like a constant,
but its value can be changed.
Let's just leave it at that, okay?
So that's it.
Okay, now that we talked a little bit about variables,
let's talk about functions.
So I didn't specify exactly what this is
just because we hadn't really come to functions,
but a function is a body of code,
is a grouping of a series of lines of code,
one to N number, N lines of codes
that is logically grouped.
And it has a few properties.
One is its return value here indicated by void.
The other part of its information is its name
followed by a pair of parenthesis,
an open parenthesis and a closed parenthesis
in which you will write something
called the function arguments or parameters.
It's pretty much just like imagine like a box
where you input things in it.
It does some processing and then it outputs that stuff,
whatever it wants to output.
So what we could do here is to create
a very simple function for ourselves.
As you saw before, or as I mentioned before,
what you write for a function in the beginning
is this data type.
I mean, what data comes out of this function.
And here, let's say we wanna add someone's first name
and their last name with a space between it.
So if I say foo as the first name and bar as the last name,
then the full name should be foo bar
and with a space in between.
So as I said, then you need to specify the data type first,
what you're gonna return.
And if you looked at the documentation
that I provided earlier,
there's a data type called string,
which is a series of characters.
Basically it can be a name, a family name,
the dress of your house or whatever.
And that data type is string.
Okay, so we say we're outputting string.
And then you say, okay, what should this function be called?
There's a convention in Dart
that your functions should follow camel case
naming convention, basically.
Camel cases, if you, for instance, say in English,
my function should be called get full name.
That's my function name,
but you cannot have spaces in your function names in Dart
or pretty much every program language that I know about.
Then remove all the spaces.
And then except for the first word,
change all the other words first letter to uppercase.
So it was like this before,
you could actually change them to uppercase first
and then remove the spacing.
So this is how you should write your function names.
This is called camel case.
Get full name, okay.
And we said that we also have to open parenthesis.
Now, let's just say then here,
we need to specify some kind of function.
We need to specify somehow
that we're gonna accept the first name and the last name.
Well, what kind of a data type does a first name have?
Well, it's kind of like a string.
It's a name.
It's a series of characters.
So let's just type string here.
And then we wanna take a first name
and we know about camel case now.
So let's just say first name is uppercase
and remove the spacing.
So first name.
Hey, that's the parameter.
And then you wanna go to the next parameter.
So just say comma.
And then you wanna say string last name.
You take the first name and the last name.
Now, we also said that after the parenthesis,
after you have accepted your parameters,
you wanna go and create like your curly brackets here.
I don't know actually if I mentioned that before,
but every function is either its body or its logic.
It's either followed by equal graded unsigned,
which we're gonna talk about later
or is by curly brackets.
So we're just gonna use curly brackets.
Now, what you wanna do here,
you wanna take the first name
and add a space to the first name
and then follow that by the last name.
So you need to tell Dart
that that is the data you wanna return.
And thankfully, there is a keyword called return
that tells Dart
that you wanna return some value from a function.
So then what you're gonna do,
you're gonna say, I wanna return what?
The first name and I wanna add a space.
Single quotes, the space, us, last name, right?
So, I mean, this is a very simple implementation
of get full name.
So, however, there's actually a better way
of doing this in Dart
and I'll explain it to you right now.
And that is by formatting your strings.
So let's say that you want to basically tell Dart
kind of like how your result looks like
and you wanna ask Dart to insert the first name
and last name into that result for you.
And that's how you'll do it like this.
You say, okay, I wanna return a string.
You know, we could buy the single quotation marks here.
And you can also do a string in Dart
with double quotation marks,
but I'm gonna explain that a little bit later.
So let's say that you want to return
the first name in here.
But if you say first name,
what's gonna happen here is that it's actually gonna return
what's gonna happen here is that it's actually gonna take
this first name as you've written in the string.
So when you get this return value,
it's actually gonna say first name,
not the value that you pass to this.
I know it may be a little bit difficult to understand
when I say the value that you pass to this.
What does it even mean?
So let's put this actually to test first, okay?
Go now into this build function,
as you can see here on line 16.
Now it may not be on line 16 for you,
but for me it is at the moment on line 16.
Just find this class my app stateless widget
and find this widget build stuff that's written there.
Create a new line here, okay?
And just say full name or sorry, say print.
As I'm writing it here, print.
And then just say, what do we call our function?
Get full name.
See here?
And it says, okay, what's the first name?
I'll say quotation marks foo and the last name is bar
and ended with a semicolon.
So, and ignore this call for now.
Sorry, this warning avoid print calls in production code.
So, okay.
So now we're calling that function.
It's, I mean, it's called calling, it's called invoking.
It may have other names,
but usually programmers call this calling,
call the function.
And these are the parameters
that you're passing to this function, okay?
So, I mean, there are two words used for
in the programming world to explain these parameters,
like with name.
And that is called a parameter or an argument.
I mean, they're used interchangeably.
The meaning of them is kind of like getting convoluted
to the point that no one knows which one is which,
but you could just use parameter or argument
and everybody would understand what you're saying.
So, but there's a little bit of a difference,
which I'm not gonna go into the detail of,
but if someone just says call this function
with parameters or arguments,
you know at least what you're doing, okay?
Foobar.
Now we're printing its value.
All you have to do in order to execute this code
is press command S and you will see the result outputted here.
Now, what we did here,
what we did here was a very key feature in Flutter
called hot reload.
As you saw, I didn't execute my code again.
I didn't press like the run button again.
I just said save.
Now, saving in Flutter triggers an action called hot reload.
Hot reload in Flutter, it's a whole topic of its own,
which I'm not gonna go so much into detail of,
but what hot reload does really is it looks for changes
in your code hierarchy without complicating it too much.
I'm just trying to phrase my sentence right
so that it's not too complicated for this chapter.
It looks for changes that you made to the code
and executes only those changes, okay?
And in the process of executing those changes,
it might execute everything else that is in its path.
And by doing a save,
this function gets called somehow magically,
which I'm not gonna go into right now,
which in turn then calls or invokes our function
called get full name,
and its value will then be passed
into another function called print, okay?
I hope that that makes sense.
And as you can see,
the result isn't really what we expected.
It just says first name.
And that is because here we said return first name.
And as you can see,
if you put first name like this inside your string,
it becomes its own string.
It has nothing to do with this anymore.
If you remove these quotation marks, however,
then it says, oh, first name is this parameter.
You see, it actually, it highlights it.
So then if I press Command S on Mac
or Control S on Linux on Windows,
you will see full being printed to the screen, okay?
You can also say last name here and it will say bar, right?
And also notice that when I'm changing these things,
it's not executing immediately automatically
on pressing Command S.
So just keep that in mind, please.
So that's for a function.
But before we move on explaining the basics of a function,
I wanna also explain a little bit about string formatting.
And that is we said that we're gonna put first name
and a last name because this is what we did
in the beginning, first name plus space plus last name.
And this wasn't so pretty because it's like
doing string concatenation in a very old fashioned manner.
In a very old fashioned manner, yeah.
I think I said it right the first time.
But what you wanna do here is to use
Dart's built-in formatting capabilities.
And you do that by first saying that, okay,
I wanna return some sort of a string.
And I wanna have first name, space, last name.
But as you saw this earlier, if I Command S or Control S,
it just returns those strings exactly as I've written them,
not the parameters.
What you can do is just to put a dollar before them.
And you can see their coloring now changes
depending on a theme that you're using
or depending on the text editor that you're using.
If you're using Android Studio,
it may not color it the same way.
Or if you're using Visual Studio Code
with a different theme on a different maybe platform,
it may not even change the color.
But for me, at least you can see that the colors change.
So as to indicate that now I'm not actually returning
the string exactly as you wrote,
except returning the parameters that are here.
So Command S.
And now you can see that the result is full bar.
Okay.
So that is the basics of functions in Dart.
Before we move on from functions,
I also wanna explain quickly that
a function doesn't necessarily have to return anything.
And that means that you may have a function here
that wants to just print some data to the screen
or to here to the debug console.
And you could just call it print my name
and parenthesis and curly brackets.
And as you can see here,
I can just write the name of the function
without any data type to be returned.
But it's a little bit of a convention
that you actually tell Dart that this is a void function.
Meaning void is a keyword,
as we talked about it earlier
in the beginning of this chapter.
Void is a keyword telling Dart
that this is a function that doesn't return anything.
And as you can see,
Dart is completely fine with this function
being completely empty.
Meaning that, well, yeah,
you said you are not returning anything.
You're probably just gonna do some stuff in here.
So I'm not gonna bother you with some errors saying that,
oh, you forgot to do something.
But as soon as you change the return value
or the return data type of your function
to, for instance, string,
then you'll get an error saying that,
oh, yeah, the body might complete normally
causing null to be returned, blah, blah.
You don't have to know exactly what that means.
But essentially what that means
is you're telling Dart that you're returning a string,
but you're not returning anything.
It's literally looking for the return keyword saying that,
oh, you missed it.
So you could silence that error
by saying return an empty string, a semi-call.
So I think this pretty much explains the basics
of functions, to be honest with you.
There's lots more to learn about functions.
And as I said,
functions can also be written using this syntax.
And this syntax is used
when your function is very simple
or in that it doesn't need to break
into different lines of code by a semi-colon.
So a function who has a very simple logic,
you can just skip writing these square brackets,
no, curly brackets, sorry.
And you can just say, you see, I will remove this,
put equal sign, greater than sign,
remove the closing curly bracket,
and then you can remove the return statement, and that's it.
That is a short hand, it's a function shorthand in Dart.
And you could use it simply to simplify kind of your code.
Some people may like it,
some people kind of may be against it,
just because it kind of splits your code
into two different styles.
Some functions are with curly brackets,
some functions are with this pointer thingy.
And kind of depends on you and your team, to be honest.
I know usually from my experience,
usually we software developers like to follow a convention.
So in one project, the developers may decide,
okay, we're just gonna go with this convention.
And since using curly brackets engulfs the ability
to have both complicated and simple return statements
in a function, it's actually preferred as a convention
than using this syntax simply because this syntax
doesn't allow you to split your code
into separate lines of code.
It has to all be in one statement.
So if that makes any sense.