This massive Flutter course will take you from being an absolute beginner to being able to
release apps on the Google Play Store and the App Store. Vandad is a very experienced
software developer and an excellent teacher. Hello everyone and welcome to this free Flutter
course. My name is Vandad and I'm a Google Developer Expert for Flutter and Dart.
Let's jump right in. Who is this course for? I designed this course mainly for absolute
beginners, so whoever hasn't even done a written a single line of code before.
I actually, when designing this course, I designed it for two specific personas. One was a graphic
designer who was working mainly with Figma. Actually, it doesn't really matter what graphical
tool you're using, Photoshop or Figma or whatever or Sketch. And the other persona was a project
manager who's mainly working with Jira. So I made the assumption that you pretty much don't know
anything about software development from before. And even if you're a software developer, you could
perhaps jump over the things that you might know. But if you haven't done
Flutter development from before, I strongly suggest that you actually follow the chapters
chronologically, which is the way I've designed this course basically. So as I mentioned,
when I designed this course, I wanted everybody to just follow the chapters one at a time and one
after each other chronologically. So I highly recommend that you don't jump over chapters just
because there's so much information provided in each chapter. And I will be referring back to
information that I provided in previous chapters in each chapter. So I think it's very good if you
can just follow the course the way I designed it to be consumed, which is chronologically.
And what you learn in this course is not only the basics, but you'll also go from a complete
beginner to being able to release your applications in Apple's App Store and Google's
Play Store. And we're going to be using a blend of different tools and software. We're going to be
using Visual Studio Code. We're using Firebase for the backend, which I'll teach you all about.
We're using even Figma as a graphic designer to create our icons and screenshots and even our
loading screens. So there's lots to be learned. And I'll take you through those steps. And I don't
make any assumptions about what you may know from before. So I'll explain everything along the way.
So you'll go from absolute beginner to being able to actually release your two applications,
which is the same code base in Apple's App Store and Google's Play Store. If you're attending this
course, please do follow me on social media. And I'd really appreciate it. I'm Van.np on Twitter.
And also you can find me by my full name on LinkedIn. That'd be much appreciated.
This course, of course, for free. But for those who want to and are able to support me,
then you can do that by buying me a cup of coffee on buymeacoffee.com. So without further ado,
let's just jump right into it. Hello, everyone, and welcome to the first chapter of our Flutter
course. There are so many different topics that I could choose for the first chapter.
And they're all very important. However, after going through the material that I've been
preparing for you for this course, I realized that one of the absolute basic points that we
have to go through is the developer accounts for Apple and Google. Now, if you're not familiar
with the term of developer account, there are basically what a developer account allows you to
do is to release your applications on Apple's App Store and Google's Play Store. As I mentioned
in the introduction, you may choose to follow along this course without actually releasing the
application to the App Store and the Play Store. But even if you do decide to not release the
applications on the aforementioned stores, you will still, for the optimal experience of development
for iOS and Android, you will most definitely need a developer account. And the reason behind that
is, I mean, it is quite deep to try to explain the actual reason behind it. But from my perspective,
one of the most important reasons you may want to have a developer account is to create the so-called
app IDs. So every application on iOS and every application on Android has an identifier,
which is usually something called a reverse domain identifier. And it's kind of like,
I still find it strange the way it is, but somewhere, somehow it was decided that every
application needs to have an identifier and every identifier is kind of like associated with a
domain name. And a domain name is kind of like a website. For instance, if you have
yourname.com as your website, then you would say that, okay, I'm going to create an application
for iOS and Android in Flutter, and I'm going to call it foobar. Then it was somehow decided
that your application's identifier would then in that case be, if you reverse it,
then it would literally be your domain in reverse, which would be com.yourname.yourapplicationsname.
I don't really know. I mean, if somebody knows the reason behind it, I would be glad to hear that.
And I'm sure that there's resources out there explaining why that is the case, but it kind of
feels like it's become the norm and we just have to roll with it. So the reason I explained the
app identifier is that when you set up your backend later, when we set up the backend later
together, in that the client that we write in Flutter is going to talk with our backend
store the notes, retrieve the notes, create a user, sign in with a user, et cetera, et cetera,
that backend setup also will require you to have your app identifier. And
even though you don't necessarily need to have a developer account to get an app identifier,
because an app identifier is just something that you decide, okay, here's my app identifier.
I think my website is called this, blah, blah. And even though you actually need a website,
that's the thing, but an app identifier is usually associated with a website. So don't
worry about it. You don't have to have a website in order to follow along with these steps that I'm
going to name here, but it is still good practice to create your developer account in order to
officially register your app identifiers. And another reason that you will need a
developer account for Apple and Google is that you will, for Apple, if you want to be able to
deploy your application onto a telephone and not use a simulator,
then you will need to register a developer account and use some resources that Apple provides you
in forms of certificates and keys and profiles in order to deploy your application to a telephone
or an iPad, for instance. In Android, the world is a little bit different in that you don't have
to do the same process, but in order to then submit your application to Google for review,
later, so that it can be available for everybody who has an Android telephone
or a tablet, you will still need a developer account. So it goes without saying that it is
a very important step that even if you decide not to deploy your application later to App Store and
Play Store, it's still a very fundamental step. So I suggest that you actually go through these
steps that I'm going to provide you in the first chapter. And that's why I actually decided to have
this as chapter one. Sorry, I have to just edit my notes a little bit. If you haven't watched the
introduction to this course, and you're just jumping here, I suggest that you go to the
introduction and watch it. I know it was about 34 minutes. It was quite a long introduction,
but there were so many important points that I feel everybody needs to know before you get
started with the course. So please watch those. If you see me moving my head around, then you know
the reason. And I explain a lot of things that are like the fundamentals of this course and the
reasoning behind all those decisions, which I believe are so important that I still suggest
everybody watched an introduction before they actually start with the course. So we've now
talked about the basics. And if you go to why we need a developer account, I believe I've already
covered this in that the developer account is the utility is an account that you register for Apple
and Google that gives you extra resources as a developer in order to be able to deploy your
test and deploy your applications to the respective app stores.
Now, if we talk about developer accounts, there are two main types of developer accounts. One is
an individual account, and the other one is a company account. And for me, the biggest
difference between these two different accounts is the liability. And by liability, I mean, if you
register an individual account, then you as an individual are liable for that application. And
as users download your application and interact with it, if they have any problems and if, for
instance, there's any judiciary problems, like if someone for some reason believes that you're
storing their data in the wrong way or that you're storing their personal information without
exposing that and telling the users about that, then they can personally hold you liable for,
for instance, breach of information or GDPR infringements or whatever it is. So
just know that you can register yourself as an individual for both Apple's App Store and Google's
Play Store, but you need to also be aware that should you wish to do that, then you're personally
liable for any problems that may be occurring in the future. So that's the personal account
or an individual account. And as a company account, then you kind of like, based on what
type of company you've created, you may or may not be personally liable for any damages that may
be caused to your users and if they bring it up to you. Now, I know this is all sounding a lot
serious. In reality, what we are trying to do is not that big a deal, but we are still trying to
store. I mean, the goal of this course is to go through an application and create an application
that can store users' notes. Notes can be quite personal and you're storing those notes then
on a backend that you have full access to. So you're kind of like storing user-created data.
So it is very important that you actually treat that data correctly. Make sure that nobody
except those who are authorized can access that data. So from a responsibility point of view,
it is actually a little bit different what kind of company account you want to create, if that's
what you want to create now. Because for instance, in Sweden, where I live, you can have a personal
company account in that, sorry, a personal company. So you can register a personal company. It
means that you are personally liable for that company. And you can also create a company that
it has like, it's like an umbrella. Basically, it sits on top and then there are people who are
directors of the company and blah, blah. So you're not personally liable.
And that is the same structure that you can find in many other countries. I believe US, Germany,
Sweden, England, many other countries, you can set up companies that are either sole proprietorship
or something called, English is not my first language, but it's something like that. Or you
can create like a limited company that you have limited liability and you're not personally liable.
So these are the different types of developer accounts that you can set up.
So we can, I mean, that point, I think we all understand now that you can create
individual or a company account. Now, I think, I mean, I personally registered already an account
as an iOS developer and an Android app developer. So,
and since I registered a company account, I can't go through setting up the exact same company again,
but at least I can show you some of the steps involved in creating those accounts.
So what we could do is to, now you can't see the screen right now, but I will bring it up here
so that you can also see. Now I'm going to bring my studio here and I'm going to make this screen
a little bit bigger so that you can see my screen better. So let me also make this a little bit
smaller on top so that you can see the content a little bit better.
So you can see here that there are two options available to you. Either you enroll as an individual
or you enroll as an organization. And it is strongly recommended actually.
So you need to make sure that you have two-factor authentication turned on.
And so that's not a problem. All this means basically as an individual, it means that just
you will need an account. You will need to set up an account. However, if you want to set up as an
organization, like if you have a limited company and you want to create an Apple developer account
that is linked to that organization, it's a little bit different because you will need to set up
something called a duns or duns or I don't know how you want to pronounce it D-U-N-S.
Which is kind of like, it's a new thing for me at least, but it is an identifier for your company
that you either have been assigned to already. I think there is a company called DMB.
So if you go to, let me see if I can bring the notes for that.
Let's see. Learn more. If you go to learn more here. Here, DMB is called by Don and Bradstreet.
So there then we have the ability to register a D-U-N-S number.
For me, I was one of the lucky people to have already been assigned a D-U-N-S number for my
company by DMB because you either have, let's see if they write it here.
You see it says DMB may have already assigned your organization a free
D-U-N-S number. Before enrolling, look up your organization to see if you have a D-U-N-S number.
So you can just click on the link and we can go here and you can then select your region. For me,
it would be Sweden. Then I would write my company name, some address information, contact information,
etc. Then you can check whether there is a D-U-N-S number assigned to your company.
So I suggest that you actually do this by going to this website.
So that's for a D-U-N-S number if you already have one, but if you don't have one,
then you will have to create and request a D-U-N-S number from DMB. I would show you the website for
DMB and D-U-N-S number right now, but my browser is set up so that my locale is already provided to
the browser, which is Swedish. Then if I go to the DMB website, you're going to see everything in
Swedish. That doesn't make any sense just to read the information in Swedish. I believe you can go
to DMB's website. So if I search for a DMB, D-U-N-S or D-U-N-S are here. So this is a Swedish
localized website for DMB. Let's see if it can change the language.
Actually, I can see here that they're very, they're actually in Sweden.
And I wonder if we can, here, change country. Let's just say
international.
So if we go here, let's see if we can,
if there's any way to actually request a D-U-N-S number, like if you say D-U-N-S.
And I can't see anything related to that, to be honest with you. So if we go back
here, I can see, I can request the D-U-N-S and here the locale is S-V-S-E. And here,
the locale was E-N-G-B. So what happens if we just go back to this URL that we were on before,
and then I just change the locale? Does that work? Well, unfortunately. But, I mean, here,
D-U-N-S number, get a D-U-N-S number. Okay, that's good. And then, and you can here say,
I'm an Apple developer, press continue. Oh, it sends you back here. That was really bad.
So it says, look up your organization in Apple's website. And when you try to get a D-U-N-S number,
it tells you to go to Apple's website. If we say that, then okay, legal business name, etc., etc.
Then okay, legal business name, etc., etc. Okay, so you will need to go through this process,
which doesn't seem to be completely easy to get a D-U-N-S number. You see, request the D-U-N-S
number. So you probably just want to go to dmb.com, it's like d-u-n-s-number.html. And I can't
explain this complete process, to be honest with you, because first of all, it will be a waste of
time for both of us. Because these are so many moving parts and a third party company that I
have no control over. So if I even try to explain their process, it may change tomorrow. So there's,
it's not a good investment of our time. But everybody else has figured it out. And I'm
pretty sure that if you just go and say, request the D-U-N-S number, you can just
follow the process and then get your D-U-N-S number. But begin by going through,
look up your organization. So you may already have been assigned a free D-U-N-S number. So
do that first, please. But if you have to request the D-U-N-S number, I believe there is a little
bit of a cost to it. And that is about $70. If I'm 70 to $80 at the time of recording this video.
So count with almost about $100. And hopefully not more, hopefully actually a lot less, but around
$70 at least. Does that make sense? I said so many numbers, $70 at least. So try to get your
D-U-N-S number. At least that that's what Apple says you will need. Now, of course, if you want
to register as a company, I can't stress this enough. You will need a website. I remember vividly
when I registered a developer account at Apple and they rejected my request saying that, well,
your website doesn't have any content. And they were right because I just created an empty website,
like a domain. I know I didn't actually create an empty website. I registered a domain.
And there was no website. So when you typed my website's name, it would just not show you anything.
And they came back and said, no, your application is rejected because you don't have a website.
What kind of company are you? So then I had to actually get like a hosting service and I have
some content in there, have like a support. So if you are registering as a website, sorry,
as a company and as an organization, you will need a hosting service. You will need a domain
provider. You will need to ensure that you have a website because they're not the same thing. If
you have a host and you have a domain provider, it still doesn't mean that you have content
on your web page. But what I realized is that if you register your domain and have a hosting
service, make sure that you have a website. Just have some content in there and say, hello,
we are this business, that business. We work with this and this. If you have any questions,
contact this email. And here's our phone number. Here's their address, et cetera. So
you need to ensure that if you have an organization, it is actually an organization. It's not just like,
hi, my name is Fubar. I'm sitting at home. Contact me if you have any questions. Not like that.
So and of course, after you made your decision, you start the enrollment process. So
now learn more, continue enrollment on the web you can do. And then you come here and you will
basically need to provide your information and continue with the process. Now we're not going
to go through this, but the important thing I have to mention here is that as you go through
the enrollment process, as an Apple developer, unfortunately, there is a cost last time, which
is about a few months ago when I registered, or I had to renew my registration. You have to renew
your registration for Apple's developer account. You have to renew it every year. And as I've
mentioned here, the process is not free, unfortunately. It costs, or last time I
registered or renewed my registration, it costs $99. And I believe it's been $99 for a very long
time. So if you're in Sweden, it costs about a thousand crowns. If you're in England, it probably
costs about 80 pounds or something. And in the US it's about, yeah, just count with almost $100. So
I used to be able to provide this like you have to have some sort of a credit card or debit card
to be able to pay for it. So after you've done that, after you register your account as an
organization, you will have direct access then, or an immediate access to your developer account.
And you can start developing applications, et cetera, et cetera. So if you're following along
with this course and you want to deploy your application to the App Store and Play Store,
please do this first. Get your developer account either as an organization or as an individual.
Get that process out of the way because a developer account, especially if you're an
organization, as I mentioned here, is not a super fast process. I mean, when you get the account,
then it's simple. It's fast and you're in there immediately. But the process itself is a long
process. So I remember for me, it took about two weeks because I got one rejection. It took about
one week for them to review the documents again. So it's not a fast process, unfortunately. It's
like very, yeah, it's just a long, long, boring process. So get that out of the way, if you can,
please. So that's for the long and not free part for iOS. And also, one more thing that I need to
mention is that if you're registering and you want to sell applications, which is not the purpose of
this course, but if you want to sell applications, then you will have to provide some banking
and tax information. So they need to ensure that the stuff that you're selling in different
countries, the money that is then being sent to your bank account, will be accounted for when
you're paying your taxes. So, and I believe that if you're trying to sell apps on the app store,
then you will have to fill in some forms with the US tax offices. I don't even remember IRS, I think
internal revenue services or something like the IRS. I believe that you have to fill some forms,
like send the forms to them, then they will come back with some sort of identifier to you.
And then you will need to use that identifier on Apple's website in order to basically say
that, yeah, yeah, I know, I'm selling stuff in the US, I'm selling stuff in Japan, I'm selling
stuff in Sweden, Norway, but I'm going to pay taxes for them here in my country. And that's
what the form says here. Here's my name, here's my company. I'm an organization or I'm an individual,
so I have no company. My personal identification number in my country is this, is my address,
my phone number, et cetera. And then you send it to them, to IRS, and then they come back and say,
okay, now we know who you are. And here is your identifier number, like a business identifier
number, BIN or something they call it, I think. I don't remember exactly, but I believe depending
on whether you're a business or an individual, then the number is a little bit different.
So if you're a business, I think it's BIN. And if you're an individual is in, I don't know.
So I don't know what that dialogue was. Some Bluetooth devices wants to connect to my computer.
I don't know what it is. So that's that part. It can be long and it's not free. Okay.
That was a lot of information. That's for iOS. Now, what we can do now is to talk
a little bit about Android as well. And the good thing about the Android process,
like setting up your account for, as a Google developer, is that it's a lot more straightforward
as you would expect from Google. And given that they're even like sending updates to
an Android app to the Google developer console is a lot more straightforward than it is for iOS.
I don't want to scare you, but it is a fact. And you will know that later when we actually
get to the end of this course where we release the apps for iOS and Android, that it is a little
bit more straightforward for Google Play Store. But you still need to sign up for a developer
account. So I'm going to take in my notes that I've talked about that. So what we also need to know
is that there is a URL that we can go to. I'm going to copy that and paste it over here. So
you see which one I'm talking about. Over here. Then you can see that you can set up a developer
account. And once you've logged in, so I'm assuming that you're logged in, then you go to
play.google.com slash console slash user or you zero sign up where URL, it may change. So let's
just, what you can do is just a Google, Google Play Console developer account or a Google
developer account. Then you will end up in a URL that looks kind of like this. So don't count
with this URL that I mentioned here because it may change. That's what I'm saying. And
you can, as it is for iOS development, you can either set it up personally as an individual or
you can set up as an organization. Now I happen to have set it up for myself as an organization
because I do have a company here in Sweden. So it is a lot easier for me to tie all my business
relations with Apple and Google into one entity, which is my developer account for,
sorry, which is my company. So it wouldn't make so much sense for me to explain this either to go
through all the details, but if you want to set it up for yourself as an individual, just press on
get started. Or if you want to set up as an organization, just press get started there.
As you can see, you can provide information about your organization. And you can see here as well,
as soon as you say I'm an organization, then they say, okay, what's the website? So you can see if
you say, I don't have a website, we recommend adding a website that represents your organization.
Well, it kind of makes sense. I mean, if you're a company, where's your website? Every company
should have a website unless you're like a pizza restaurant or something. Even a pizza restaurant
probably needs a website, but we have a pizza restaurant here in our town that doesn't have
a website. So they're on Facebook. And you probably don't want to say that your company's
website is on Facebook. So yeah, where were we? Here. And if you say you're an individual,
then you come here and they ask for some other stuff, but still interesting because
it says enter the URL of your website or social media profile. So here you kind of have to need
to enter that as well. So maybe you can get away with a Facebook URL. I laughed about it, but
maybe you can get away with it. I don't know. But I don't recommend that, to be honest with you,
because as you will see later in the course, when we actually submit our apps to App Store and Play
Store, there are a few key data points that you have to provide to both stores. One is a privacy
policy URL, and the other one is a support URL. And there are also two other emails you have to
provide. The first one is the support email and the other one is a contact email. And if you're
setting up a business account, then I really suggest that you actually set up a website,
because if you set up a website and you have a domain, you have an email provider,
then your email will kind of be like foobar at mybusiness.com. It's a lot more professional
to set up an email that is connected to your email or to your domain than it is to say
mrjohnson at gmail.com. I wouldn't trust a business that has a gmail.com account.
I kind of want to know that, yeah, here's a serious business, that they have their own website,
and blah, blah, blah. But on the contrary, setting up a website, setting up some emails
doesn't necessarily mean you're serious either. But it makes it more dedicated, if you know what
I mean. So yeah, that's the process for setting up an account also as an Android developer.
I think that's about it. That's all I wanted to mention in this first chapter of our course.
I highly recommend that you get your developer accounts for Apple and for
Google. What you'll also need to know is that, I mean, I've talked a lot about now,
Apple account and a Google developer account, but if you're developing your application
on a Windows machine, for instance, if you're trying to learn how to develop Flutter
applications and you don't care about releasing your application at all, you don't have to do
any of this. Just follow along with the course as usual, no problem. But if you want to actually
release your application for iOS, then you most definitely need to also have a Mac because you
can't build your application otherwise. There are some tricks you can do. You can build your
Flutter application and later on, like a friend's Macintosh if they have one, or you can send it to
a service that's in the cloud and they build the app for you and then they will send it back to
you and then you can submit it. Or maybe they even have to submit it. It's a bit hairy, to be
honest with you, but it's a complicated topic. It is a little bit difficult to explain.
For instance, if you're on a Windows machine, you can't even have Xcode. Xcode is the tool
and the entire chain of tool sets that gets installed on a Macintosh in order to build
an application for iOS platform. Now, why am I talking about this? The reasoning behind that
is that if you're developing a Flutter application, then Flutter can be deployed
on a Windows machine, Macintosh, or collectively called as desktop, web, Android, iOS, five
platforms at the moment. If you're trying to release your application and build it for iOS,
for instance, and test on an iPhone or an iPad, you can't do that on a Windows machine,
unfortunately. There's nothing wrong with a Windows machine. It's just Apple's fault for
locking down their build systems and alter tools to Macintosh. They haven't made the
conscious decision or yeah, they haven't made the decision to
bring their tool system and tooling to Windows, unfortunately, or Linux. Swift,
which is the language to write native applications for iOS, can be run, I believe, on Linux.
Windows might be, but its main platform is still Mac.
I know that this is a lot of information also to learn, but if there is anything I want to
close this chapter, the first chapter of this course with is, you can learn Flutter and follow
along with the steps I'm going to provide in this course without having to register any accounts
yet. So that's point one. Point two is that you will need a Macintosh if you want to use it for
if you want to comfortably build and release your Flutter app for iOS.
If you want to release your application on Google Play Store, which is point three,
if you want to do that, you will need to register a developer account on Google Play Console,
as I've shown you here. I believe that's all. That's all you need to know. So
some of you may already have all these accounts and don't have to worry about it,
but some may not know all this. If you're coming from a design background, if all you do is work
with Figma, et cetera, this is some of the important information that you'll need to know
about because I don't want you to get frustrated during the process, so I just want you to have
some information so that you can get started at least without too much hassle. All right,
that's it, I think, for this chapter. I can take in my notes that I've explained everything
I wanted to explain. It did take about 35 minutes. It's not unexpected, to be honest.
It's a lot of information, and I kind of want to take my time with it. It's important that you
and for me as well to understand all this. So great. I think that's it for this video.
So I'll see you in the next chapter. Hi, everyone, and welcome to the second chapter of our course.
Now, if you haven't watched the introduction to this course, I really suggest that you do that
before continuing with the course because there are so many points that I'll explain in that
introduction that I believe are so important to understand before continuing with the course. So
in this chapter, what we're going to do is we're going to take care of some setup steps that are
required for pretty much the rest of this course and all the other chapters that follow
along after this one, chapter three, four, and et cetera. So we're going to talk about Flutter,
Dart, Dart Pad, how to install Flutter, whether you're on Windows, Mac, or Linux.
And we're also going to talk about Xcode, Android Studio, and we're going to talk about a few
very useful extensions to our code editor. So if you're coming from a background where you
haven't worked with any kind of programming language before, I'm going to take this chapter
quite easy. So if you're an advanced programmer already, you may want to skip this and you already
have Flutter installed, everything, you can skip this chapter without a problem. So let's start by
talking about what Flutter is. Well, traditionally developers and programmers
or software engineers, however you want to call them, they've been creating and writing code with
their fingers in different languages, and then they're targeting different platforms. It's
very important to understand what a language, programming language is versus a platform.
Think of a platform as the end station where a software ends up being run on. So let's say
Windows is a platform, Mac is a platform, Linux is a platform, and iOS that runs on all iPhones
is a platform, Android is a platform, et cetera. Now, you would have programming languages that
you as a software developer would use in order to target those platforms, to write software for
those platforms. So you use a programming language in order to write a piece of code
and be able to run that code on that target platform. So the programming language example
is JavaScript, Python, Swift, Rust. What else is popular right now? Java, Kotlin, all these.
These are programming languages. So you as a software developer who's trying to learn
Flutter would use then Dart as your programming language, as I will soon explain. So
that has been the tradition that a person sits in front of a computer and says,
okay, I want to write a program for Windows. Then they go and write some code maybe with
Csharp.net, or maybe they will just use some other technology. I don't know what's out there
right now for Windows. Maybe they would use VB.net, and then they would be done and they
would release the software for Windows and be like, okay, I'm done. Now, then someone comes
into the project and says, oh, we need the same software for Macintosh, or we need the same software
for some other, for instance, platform. Then you would have to go and write the same software,
exact same code, pretty much, for the other platform. So this process would be very repetitive
in that you would have to write the same software over and over again. So things such as Flutter
came in in order to remedy that. So saying that a software engineer sits at home or sits in the
office, works with a group of other people and a designer maybe, or a few designers, UXer as a
product owner, et cetera. They would write the same code, which will then be run on different
platforms. So as a software developer, you wouldn't have to maintain different, very similar pieces of
code that only can be run on one specific platform. So Flutter in its ground basically is a UI
framework for writing beautiful applications that run on multiple platforms at the same time.
Developed by Google, has been in production for a very long time. It's tried and tested. It's
open source. And if you don't come from a software engineering background, open source basically
means that the code that is written for Flutter, basically the code that makes up Flutter, is open
to the public for finding bugs and also for contributing to it or maybe just learning from
it. So if you're, for instance, coming from a background of as a designer, it's kind of like
you have your Figma file open to the entire world or your Adobe XD source open to the entire world
for them to watch what you're doing as you're designing and also for them to be able to fix
stuff in your design if they see it not working as it should. So that's open source. So Flutter is
open source UI framework developed by Google. What a framework means, I mean, if you're not coming
from a software engineering background, a framework is kind of like a set of tools provided to you
as a software developer. So you can use these tools, take a bit of this one, take a bit of that
one in order to produce an output. So Flutter in itself is a software, but it's more precisely
referred to as a framework because it's a collection of tools. So if you hear framework,
just know, oh, there's a collection of things I can use to produce some output. Now,
that's what Flutter is. But what powers Flutter is a programming language called Dart. And
Dart has been in the making for more than eight years is a language that at the moment being
maintained by Google and also is open source. So anybody can contribute to it, anybody can learn
from it and find exploits or maybe problems with it and it will get patched by the public or by
Google themselves. So Dart is the language, the programming language that powers Flutter, you could
say. So now you know what Flutter is and now you know what Dart is. And I think in the next step
now what we can do is talk about a great piece of web software called Dart Pad. Now,
Dart Pad, as I said, is a web software or you could just call it a website that allows you to
run or write your Dart code, maybe pure Dart code or code for Flutter and run it directly in your
browser without you even having to install anything. So just open your browser and as you
will see soon we go to Dart Pad and you will see how it looks like. So let me just show you a little
demonstration here. So here I have Dart Pad open and I can actually increase the size so you can
see a little bit better. I may have to rearrange some components here on the screen so you can see
the screen better. So I went to dartpad.dartlang.org and you can see here that there is a program
written on the left-hand side and I can actually, yeah, let this what is Dart, Dart Pad allows you,
blah, blah, text to be there so you can have context of what I'm talking about. And you can see
that the program is sitting there and you are allowed then to either change the program the
way it is or click anywhere here to see documentation down here or press the run button.
So I'm just going to press the run button and you can see that the text hello got printed to the
screen five times plus the number of times it was actually printed. It's also printed to the screen.
So hello one, two, three, four, five. So what you see on this side is the source code if you
remember from open source. So this is the source code written in the programming language called
Dart. And this is the output of that program. So Dart Pad allows you to write text here and just
execute it and see the results immediately. So that's what Dart is. I mean, sorry, Dart Pad is.
And we're going to talk about Dart and Dart Pad more in the course. But right now what we should
do is to start by installing Flutter. Because, I mean, you could say, okay, but Flutter is just the
UI framework. How about Dart? Well, the way Flutter is packaged by default is that it includes the
Dart programming language and its runtime. So the tool is required to run any Dart code.
It packages all of that in just one big chunk for you. So you don't have to go and install
different components like install Dart separately in Flutter. So let's just then improvise. And I'm
going to say in here, let's say install Flutter. Okay? Then you go to this beautiful website called
Flutter.dev. I'm going to increase the size here so you see.
So we go there now. And you will see this beautiful website here. And what we're going to do is just
to press on get started. And remember, we pressed on get started. But this website looks like this
right now. Maybe in a few months or maybe in a few years, it will change. So you'll just have
to find out a way to get to the installation part. Right now it's called get started. And I
can see it's located as docs.flutter.dev get started install. Then pick your platform here.
I'm on a Macintosh, but if you're on a Windows, just click on Windows and then you get instructions
on how to install Flutter. And then, or if you're on Linux, you can also do the same. Just get
instructions for your platform. Now I'm on a Mac and I'm going to click on Mac. And then I'm going
to look at this information here. I'm going to increase the size so it's a little bit easier to
read. And it says, okay, download the following installation bundle to get the latest stable
release of the Flutter SDK. SDK means software development kit, I believe. So it's just like
series of tools for you to use. It's just fancy words. So then we're going to do that. Let's just
get Flutter Mac. I'm going to download it. And it may take some time because it is actually quite
a chunky bit of software. As you can see, it's almost 1.2 gigabytes. So depending on your
internet connection, it could take anything between a few seconds to a few minutes.
And after you've done that, then you will have to unzip that in some folder.
So what that means is just I can see that my Mac is already decompressing this zip file
for me. So I don't have to do that myself. And it's already decompressed in this
place. So I'm just going to click on it and I'm going to show you its content. So it looks like
this. Okay. Now that you have this, what you need to do is to ensure that all these files are
placed inside a location on your computer, which is protected so that you don't accidentally
delete it. And it's also a good, like, you know exactly where it is. So by that, I mean,
don't put it on your desktop and don't put it in like documents or anything. It's not a
document. It's a software. What I like to do is usually to have a folder on a Macintosh called
Dev. So I will open Terminal here, as you can see. Terminal, if you're not familiar with it,
is an application that you can control pretty much the entire system with it. If you're on a Mac or
if you're on Linux or any Unix based system. And if you're on Windows, you can also do a lot with
your Terminal. So in Windows, that Terminal is called CMD, I believe, as in command, I believe.
On Linux and Mac, it's called Terminal. I'm using a Terminal here called iTerm.
But if you're on Vanilla Mac OS, then you would go and open Terminal
like this, which is just looking like that.
So I'm going to open iTerm right now, which is my Terminal. You can open the Terminal that
you're comfortable with. I'm going to increase the size of this. I like to place
my installations for these pieces of software in my home directory, which is denoted by this
little funny character, slash dev. And if I look at the contents of this, I can see
if I look at the contents of this, I can see I have a folder called Toolink. If I say Toolink
and look at the contents of it, I can see Flutter is right there.
So for me, Flutter installation, this folder that got downloaded for me in my downloads folder,
I would go and copy its contents and place it in this folder. So if I say CD Flutter,
and then you can see that I'm in my user, Dev folder, Toolink, Flutter. So this is where I
choose to put Flutter. Now you can choose to put this downloaded folder anywhere else, as the
documentation tells you, in the desired location, for example. So go ahead and do that. Pick a
location. For me, this location works. For you, it may be, if you're on Windows, it would probably be
C backslash, I don't know, you could say dev backslash Toolink backslash Flutter. This could
be a good location for your Toolink or Flutter. So I'm imagining now that you've done that. You've
gotten a folder, and for me, it's this one, where you've extracted your Flutter installation in.
Now you can see that it says, in this third step, you will need to expose Flutter's binary
files to your system. And what that basically means is that Flutter as an SDK or a toolkit
or a framework, it has a lot of bits and pieces of software in it. And some of these bits are
more important in that sense that they're actually executable in that. Imagine that
on your computer, whether it's a Macintosh, Windows or Linux, you can have different
documents. Some documents can be text. Some documents can be images. Some documents can
be, I don't know what else they can be. Or a Word document, for instance. Okay,
good. I came up with another example. Or they could be programs. A program is something that
you can just double click on and a piece of software gets executed and then it will open.
For instance, an example of the program is a Microsoft Word. Another example of program is
Google Chrome web browser. Another example of program is Safari. So these are programs.
And Flutter comes also with its own built-in programs that do very specific and important
things on your computer related to Flutter, of course. Sorry, I have to see my recording studio.
Nothing you had to do. It was just for me. So these important programs that are inside
the Flutter installation, which you just downloaded, need to be exposed to your entire system
so that you can work with Flutter with ease. And that means if you're, for instance,
from a design background, it will allow you to anywhere in your terminal, just write Figma
and Figma app would open. And that's the same thing with Flutter. In this folder, you see,
we're in the Flutter folder where you downloaded your installation and installed it in this folder.
There is a folder called bin, which means binary. In here, there are so many things that are important
to the entire system to run. You see Flutter and Dart. These two, I said so many, but yeah,
there's pretty much two. So these two binary executables need to be exposed to your system.
And the way to do that on a Macintosh is to change your paths as is documented here.
So the way I like to do that is I go and change my, if I do a vim and look at my zshrc,
I can see my paths and you can see it here. So you see, I've actually put that export command
as it is stated here. I put it here, you see. This may be a bit intimidating, to be honest with you.
Well, all it's doing is that you see this file that I've placed here, I don't know if I can
actually zoom into it. And if you can see, I don't know how that looked in the actual recording,
but this is sort of like a set of instructions to my terminal on this Macintosh to tell it
where different bits and pieces of binary executables are placed, such as Flutter,
Dart, Python, et cetera, et cetera. So when I install a piece of software in this way,
you see, we just downloaded a package and just put it somewhere on our computer.
Macintosh won't know about the stuff that's in it. Of course it won't. So you have to tell it
where those things are. Because otherwise, if you don't do this step, if you don't do the step three,
then every time you want to run Flutter, then you have to specify exactly where that Flutter command
is. So for me, it would be my home folder, dev tooling Flutter bin slash Flutter. But if you do
this, then you can anywhere in your terminal, just write Flutter and your Macintosh or Linux or
Windows computer will know where to find it. So do that. Put these instructions as specified here
in your path. And after doing that, you may need to reload your path using a command on Windows and
Linux called source and VSHRC for me. Depending on which shell you have, you may have to
put that instruction in somewhere else. On Windows, I believe you will have to modify your
environment variables. I remember this from many, many years ago. Let's see if you have to do that.
Update your path, you see. If you wish to run Flutter commands in regular Windows console,
take these steps, blah, blah. From the start search, end and select edit environment variables
for your account. So what you'll just have to do, really, is just to follow these steps. I mean,
I'm going through basically giving you some of the basics of these instructions so you can get
like a head start. But these instructions can also change in the future. So don't rely just on what
I'm telling you, please. Just go to the installation website here as you see docs.flutter.dev. Get
started and install.